潘多拉的森林中…
The forests of Pandora…
有许多危险
hold many dangers.
但潘多拉最危险的一点…
But the most dangerous thing about Pandora…
是你会不知不觉爱上这里
is that you may grow to love her too much.
我们用乐珠来记事
We sing the songcords to remember.
每一颗乐珠都是一段故事
Each bead, a story in our life.
这一颗 纪念儿子出生
A bead for the birth of our son.
奈特亚
Neteyam!
这一颗是指我们领养的女儿 琪莉
A bead when we adopted our daughter, Kiri.
她亲生母亲是格蕾丝
Born of Grace's avatar.
这孩子的亲生父亲却完全是个迷
A daughter whose conception was a total mystery.
纪念和艾娃的初次交流
A bead for the first communion with Eywa.
族人说 我们与艾娃共生
The People say we live in Eywa…
艾娃也与我们同在
and Eywa lives in us.
圣母艾娃
The Great Mother
她的心中放着所有的儿女
holds all her children in her heart.
准备了
syal!
幸福很简单
Happiness is simple.
感受风向
Hufwe!
谁能想到一个大兵也懂得幸福呢？
But who would've thought a jarhead like me could crack the code?
坏蛋要来了
Za'u rawm!
快跑
Tul!
[外星语] 我第一次遇见你们父亲时…
[外星语] 还打算要杀他
[外星语] 那叫一见钟情
等我懂了 我已有了四个孩子
Before I knew it, we had four.
天空人被赶回了地球
When we sent the Sky People back to Earth,
留下了几个科学家
a few of 'em stayed.
因为他们喜欢纳威人
Science guys, loyal to the Na'vi.
还有一个是蜘蛛
And then there was Spider.
- 蜘蛛 蜘蛛 - 蜘蛛
- Spider, Spider… - Spider!
他被困在这儿了
He was just stuck here.
因为太小进不了冷冻舱
Too young for a cryo-capsule.
你个小野人
You little wild man.
再见 诺姆
See you, Norm!
他是战争孤儿 在实验室长大
Orphaned by the war, he was raised by the lab guys.
蜘蛛 多带点氧气
Spider, take your spare!
我就是去村里
I'm just going to the village!
他不是我们家的人
He wasn't part of our family.
他就像野猫一样到处游荡
He was like a stray cat. Just always around.
他和孩子们打成一片
Inseparable from our kids.
奈蒂莉说他永远是外星人
To Neytiri, he would always be alien.
是他们的人
One of them.
[外星语] 他应该属于他的种族
[外星语] 这是我的！
[外星语] 我先拿到的
[外星语] 我为什么要让给你？
我脑子笨 花了好几年学纳威语
Took a few years to get the language through my thick skull.
[外星语] 就是我的！
[外星语] 洛阿克 你是骗子！把它给我！
现在我听纳威语完全没有问题
But now when I hear it, it might as well be English.
我讨厌你
I hate you!
我讨厌你一百一千一万倍 洛阿克
Well, I hate you times infinity, Lo'ak!
你是个混蛋
Penis face!
别说脏话
That's enough.
不然就别玩了
Don't make me come over there.
它要从那块大石头后面出来了
He's gonna come out from behind those big rocks.
准备好
There he is.
来了 快去抓住他
There you go. Go get it!
哈哈 奈特亚 你是抓鱼大师
Hey, Neteyam, the mighty fisherman.
你真能干
There you go. Good boy.
这条鱼真大
That's a big one.
在石头后面
By the rocks.
和你说的一样
Right where you said.
他有多高？
How tall is he?
- 他有这么高 - 他很高
- He's… that tall. - He's tall!
时间过得真快
Goes by too fast.
像梦一样
Like a dream.
- 琪莉 - 哥哥 快来
- Kiri. - Bro, come on.
要拍了
Come on.
笑一笑 傻瓜
Smile, skxawng.
幸福很简单
Happiness is simple.
像约会之夜 没有孩子们打扰
Like date night. Time away from the kids.
但是幸福…
But the thing about happiness…
也可以在瞬间消失
it can vanish in a heartbeat.
夜空中多了颗星星
A new star in the night.
这只说明一件事
It could only mean one thing.
飞船正在减速
Ships. Decelerating.
天空人回来了
And Sky People returning.
（一年后）
脉搏168 快要醒了
Pulse 168. He's coming up…
对 他醒了
Yeah, here it comes.
你很好
You're just fine.
安静躺着
Just lie still.
不要激动
Stay calm.
对 瞳孔光感反射很好
Yep. Pupillary reflex is good.
别折腾他了
Get that out of his face.
上校
Colonel,
能听到吗？上校？
can you hear me? Colonel?
不 请您躺下
You need to lie back down, sir.
给他打麻醉 麻醉针
Sedate him! Sedate him!
快出去
Get outta here!
走走走
Go, go, go!
- 快叫保安 - 抓他胳膊
- Get security! - Grab him!
- 抓住他 - 按住他
- Grab him! - Hold him!
冷静
Calm down!
上校 冷静点
Colonel, stand down!
上校 是我
Colonel, it's me!
温弗利下士
Corporal Wainfleet!
莱尔？
Lyle?
是你吗？
That you?
是我 这是老狗
Yes, sir. And Z Dog.
那是菲克
And Fike.
好吧 放开我
I'm all right. Let me go.
我没事
I'm all right.
真好啊
Well…
这可没想到啊
ain't this a bitch.
准备 还有两分钟进入潘多拉
Stand by. Two minutes to Pandora insertion.
准备开始减速
Secure for Delta V.
好的 脐带分离
All right. Umbilical's clear.
血氧数值89
Pulse ox 89.
我来说明一下
In case you haven't figured it out yet,
你就是迈尔斯·夸里奇上校
you're Colonel Miles Quaritch.
变年轻了 变高了 变蓝了
Only younger, taller, bluer,
没原来那么帅气了
and not nearly as good-lookin'.
两小时后 我就要全副武装去空袭纳威人的要塞
In two hours, I fly a mission against the Na'vi's stronghold.
上面的人觉得我应该谨慎些 给自己留个备份
The powers that be thought it prudent that I do this backup…
以防万一
just in case.
既然你看到了这段录像
And if you are watchin' it, well,
那说明我已经完事大吉了
it means that I did get my ticket punched.
嘿 帕克
Hey, Parker,
我接下来还要说点什么？
just what the hell am I supposed to say now?
就告诉他复制的流程
Just remind him how this works.
- 谁？ - 这里
- Who? - Here.
看到这个了吗？这里面是你的记忆和人格
So see this? This is all your memories and your personality.
我们会把这个送回地球
We're gonna send this back to Earth…
- 此刻你的身体还泡在培养舱里 - 好了 了解
- where you're growing in a lab as we speak. - All right, I got it.
把这东西放进去就可以…
We're gonna imprint you with it, and then…
- 到底是我说还是你说？ - 好的 快说吧
- Am I doin' this, or are you doin' this? - Hurry it up. Hurry it up.
总之 克隆我们是
Anyway, the idea is…
为了保存潘多拉项目上最强毅的几个人
to get the minds of the saltiest on-world operators.
比方说 那个是温弗利下士…
Yeah, like Corporal Wainfleet over there and…
你的谦逊的解说员被装进
your humble narrator into…
合成的身体
recombinant bodies.
你是个合成体 上校
You're a recom now, Colonel,
拥有我的全部记忆和全部的魅力
loaded with my memories and my charm.
你不会记得我死过一次
What you won't remember is my death…
因为老子还没死呢
because it hasn't happened yet,
而且也不会死
and it ain't gonna.
- 说得没错 - 当然了
- Damn right. - Hell yeah.
不管发生什么
Well, whatever happened,
既然你就是我 麻烦你替我报仇
if you're any clone of mine, you'll be lookin' for some payback.
杰克·萨利是复仇名单的第一位
And Jake Sully would be at the top of that list.
记住孩子
Remember, kid,
海军陆战队永不言败
a Marine can't be defeated.
就算你杀死我们
Oh, you can kill us,
我们也能从地狱爬出来
but we'll just regroup in hell.
忠诚永在
Semper fi.
地面队 上
Ground team, go!
拿上这个 走
Take this! Go!
准备 两分钟后 出发
Let's go. Two minutes, people. Let's go.
哥哥 我们也去下面看看
Bro, we have got to get down there.
不行 爸爸会揍扁我们的
No way! Dad will skin us!
你来不来 胆小鬼
Come on. Don't be a wuss.
洛阿克
Lo'ak!
快点回来 你…
Get back here, you…
连箱子带走
Taking the whole case!
弹匣 火箭筒 防空导弹都拿走
We're taking mags, the RPGs, the stingers.
- 哥哥 走 快点 - 洛阿克
- Bro, let's go. Come on! - Lo'ak!
奈特亚 我们走
Okay, let's go!
洛阿克
Lo'ak!
给 拿上
Move! Take that!
拿好武器 给你 出发
Take these weapons. Here, boy. Go!
洛阿克
Lo'ak!
这东西你还不会用呢
You don't even know how to use it.
爸爸教我了
Dad taught me.
武装直升机 撤开
Gunship's inbound! Fall back!
哥哥 快来
Bro, come on!
洛阿克 你在哪儿？
Lo'ak, where are you?
奈特亚
Neteyam!
没事 没事 你没事吧？
Easy, easy, you okay?
- 没事 - 你哥哥在哪儿？
- Yeah. - Where's your brother?
- 那边 - 他在哪儿？
- That way. - Where is he? Where?
你快离开这 快点
Get outta here! Go on!
奈特亚
Neteyam!
啊 不
Oh, no.
不不不
Oh, no, no, no.
天呐
Oh, God.
爸爸
Dad?
你来这儿干什么
What are you doin' here, boy?
没长脑子吗？
What the hell were you thinkin'?
我 对不起
I'm s… I'm sorry.
抱歉 长官
I'm sorry, sir.
我们已经不在堪萨斯
We are not in Kansas anymore.
我们要去潘多拉星球
We are going to Pandora.
好了
Now,
我知道你们所有人心里都在想同一个问题
I know you're all askin' yourselves the same question.
为什么这么蓝过？
Why so blue?
我们上辈子犯了罪
For our sins in our past life,
现在受到惩罚 变成了敌人的样子
we have been brought back in the form of our enemy.
和他们一样 高大 有力 敏捷
That gives us their size, their strength, their speed.
还有 经过训练
And with our training,
我们会变得更强
that's a pretty potent mix.
我们有任务吗？
Do we have a mission yet?
当然有
Indeed we do.
任务是找到并且除掉
Our mission is to hunt down and kill
纳威叛乱行动的首领
the leader of the Na'vi insurgency.
纳威人称他托鲁克马克多（魅影骑士）
The one they call Toruk Makto.
杰克·萨利
Jake Sully.
没错
Yeah!
这才像话
That's what it is!
进攻 进攻
Attack, attack!
打中了
Got ya!
图克 别这样
Tuk! Come on!
我涂成蓝色跑得更快了
I'm definitely faster when I'm blue.
傻瓜
Skxawng.
是真的
No, seriously.
动物也都对我更好了
And the animals respect me more.
它们认不出我是人类
They don't think of me as human.
等等 你是人类？
Wait. You're human?
他们来了
They're coming!
（高地营地 奥马蒂卡雅族堡垒）
他们来了
They're coming!
琪莉 蜘蛛
Kiri, Spider!
战斗小队已经回来了
The war party's coming back!
快来 快来呀
Come on, come on.
去看看 走
Let's go, come on.
- 妈妈 - 图克
- Mom! - Tuk…
- 妈妈 - 图克 图克 图克
- Mom. - Tuk, Tuk, Tuk, Tuk, Tuk.
列队
Fall in.
你们的任务是观察
You're supposed to be spotters.
空中有异样就叫人来
You spot bogeys, and you call 'em in.
在远处观察
From a distance!
你们听不懂吗？给我过来
Does any of this sound familiar? Get here!
我把重要的任务交给你们俩
Jesus. I let you two geniuses fly a mission,
你们竟然擅自行动
and you disobey direct orders.
琪莉 你去帮外婆照顾伤员 好吗？
Kiri, can you go help your grandmother with the wounded? Please?
我哥哥就受伤了
My brother is wounded.
- 好 - 孩子 快去吧
- It's fine. - Baby girl, please.
- 图克 你也去 去吧 - 爸爸
- Tuk, go with her. Go. - Dad.
长官 我 这都是我的责任
Sir. I take full responsibility.
我没错 你的责任
Yeah, you do. That's right.
因为你是哥哥
'Cause you're the older brother.
就得有哥哥的样子
You gotta act like it.
亲爱的
MaJake.
你的儿子还在流血呢
Your son is actually bleeding.
妈妈 没关系 我…
Mother, it's fine. I…
快去包扎吧 原地解散
Just go and get patched up. Go on, dismissed.
你不知道吗？
You do understand
你差点就把你哥哥害死
that you almost got your brother killed.
我知道
Yes, sir.
你被禁飞了 禁飞一个月
You're grounded. No flying for a month.
去照看伊卡兰 不许偷懒
Now, see to the ikran. All of 'em.
是
Yes, sir.
把你的脸擦干净
And get that crap off your face.
要不要给你吹吹？
Aw, want a kiss on the boo-boo?
- 给他这个 - 好
- Give him this. - Okay.
要是我就用亚娜树
I would use yalna bark.
喝了吧
Here, drink.
哦 是吗？
Oh, you would?
谁是大祭司？
And who is Tsahik?
是您 外婆 让开
You are, Grand… Move!
是您外婆 可亚娜树的疗效更好
You are, Grandmother. But yalna bark is better.
刺痛感比较轻
It stings less.
你可真勇敢
Mighty Warrior.
怎么了？
What?
奈特亚和洛阿克想要以你为榜样
Neteyam and Lo'ak try to live up to you.
这对他们来说很难的
It is very hard on them.
我知道
I know.
你对他们太严厉了
You are very hard on them.
我是父亲 我有责任
I'm their father. It's my job.
我们不是军队
This is not a squad.
我们是一家人
It is a family.
我还以为他们回不来了
I thought we'd lost them.
- 明天再见 - 哎 你们好吗？
- We'll check on this tomorrow. - Hey, man. How's it going?
蜘蛛
Spider.
- 做个好梦 - 打你的屁股
- Stream. - Your ass is mine.
那你来啊
I'm right here.
你好啊
What's up, bro?
阿凡达以外的人都出去
Avatars only, go around!
抱歉
Sorry.
行了 涂一身蓝你也不会长高的
Yeah. Those blue stripes don't make you any bigger, bro.
那你也不是我的对手
Yeah, well, I can still kick your ass.
这一天过得
Hell of a day.
真长啊
Long run.
像一只烦人的小虫
Like a little annoying bug.
是啊 都快烦死我了
Real hysterical, guys.
最不公平的是
You know what really sucks though?
你们可以呼吸地球空气几小时
Is you can breathe Earth air for hours,
而我在外面呼吸几秒 就晕过去了
and I can only breathe your air for, like, 10 seconds.
是啊 小猴子 你可真是不幸
Yeah, Monkey Boy, that really sucks.
活该
For you.
- 嘿 麦克斯 - 你们好
- Hi, Max. - Hey, kids.
- 你好吗 麦克斯 - 你们好
- What's up, Max? - What up?
- 嘿 诺姆 - 洛阿克
- What's up, Norm? - Lo'ak.
你好 妈妈
Hi, Ma.
也许是我在这儿已经疯了
Maybe I'm just losing it out here,
但真的有证据显示
but I'm seeing real evidence…
整个星球会做出反应来应对刺激
of a systemic response on a global level.
我不能…
I can't…
我先不说星球有“智慧” 可是…
I won't use the term "intelligence." It's, um…
也许可以说它“有意识”
maybe "awareness" is a better word.
就好像潘多拉星的整个生态圈
It's like the entire biosphere of Pandora
是有意识的
is aware…
它有自己的认知还能做出回应
and capable of this cognitive response.
噢 完了 我不能那么说
Oh, crap, I can't say that.
他们会折磨我
They'll crucify me.
我得说一些…
I mean, I need to say something that'll…
你说 谁让她怀孕的？
So who do you think knocked her up?
肯定是诺姆
Pretty sure it was Norm.
太对了
Totally.
要我说你们两个都去死吧
You do not deserve to live.
不不不 想想看 好吗？
No, no, no. Think about it, right?
诺曼是个好学生
I mean, he's the teacher's pet.
天天跟格蕾丝泡在实验室
He's out at the lab with her all the time.
那我就还不如自杀
I would kill myself.
或者喝毒药死了才好
I would drink acid.
洛阿克说得对 每段录像都有他
Bro, you're right. He's, like, in every shot.
你看 他还对人家抛媚眼呢
Bro, look, look, he's giving her looks.
说不定有一天
See, I'm thinkin'…
他俩的阿凡达出去散步 孤男寡女的…
their two avatars were out in the woods all alone…
恶心
Gross!
行了
Guys.
找出你的亲生父亲也不一定是好事
I mean, sometimes it's not so great to know who your father was.
没事
Whatever.
我都不记得了
Don't even remember him.
- 蜘蛛 - 行了
- No, Spider. - Dude.
蜘蛛
Spider…
你是你 他是他
You are not him.
（桥头堡市）
走走走 直接进航空站
Go, go, go! Directly inside the terminal.
别停下
Do not stop.
快
Move!
摘面罩
Masks off.
长官 这位是将军
Sir, this is the General.
阿德莫尔将军
General Ardmore.
幸会 上校
Good to meet you, Colonel.
我听说了
I've heard good things,
但你走后 这里变了很多
but a lot's changed since your last tour here.
跟我来
Walk with me.
新的指挥中心在这边
The new ops center is over here.
刚刚投入使用
That just came online.
这些组装机器人六天就能盖一座建筑
These Swarm Assemblers, they can put up a building in six days.
去年一年我们的建设成果比前三十年都多
We have done more here in a year than in the previous 30 years.
我们不是来挖矿的
We're not here to run a mine, Colonel.
作为外驻指挥官
As On-World Commander,
我接到了更重要的任务
I have been charged with a greater mission.
地球要完了
Earth is dying.
我们的任务是征服前方这片土地
Our task here is to tame this frontier.
也就是说让潘多拉星成为人类新的家园
Nothing less than to make Pandora the new home for humanity.
但是搬进新家之前
But before we can do that,
得先让这里的敌人闭嘴
we need to pacify the hostiles.
萨利的突袭越来越大胆 也越来越频繁
Sully's raids are becoming bolder and more frequent.
每次都是精心策划
His strikes are well-planned.
他的地面和空中行动组配合非常紧密
He's got tight coordination between his ground and air assets.
他一直在破坏我们的外部设施
His forces are hitting our outlying sites.
矿井 管线
The mines, pipelines,
想切断我们的供应链
cutting off our supply chain.
两天前他们袭击了一列磁悬浮列车
And they hit a maglev two days ago.
关于萨利的指挥中心有什么信息吗？
Any intel on Sully's base of operations?
有 显示山地
Yeah. Give me the mountains.
在哈利路亚山一个复杂的岩洞里
It's a cave system in the Hallelujah Mountains somewhere.
可是我们每次派军队过去
But every time we send our forces up there,
都有不少伤亡
we take losses.
我们的设备和武器会激怒那儿的动物
Our hardware really stirs up the hornet's nest.
进入敌方领空不到十分钟
We only get 10 minutes in enemy airspace,
它们就都扑上来了
they are all over us.
上校
Colonel,
我们认为你的蓝军小队可以伪装成土著
we believe your Blue Team will be perceived as indigenous
而不会引发生态圈的免疫反应
and will not trigger the immune response.
你打算怎么验证这个假说呢 将军？
And how might we test that hypothesis, General?
你们亲自验证
The hard way.
那太好了
Outstanding.
快要进入敌方领空了
We're entering hostile airspace.
收到
Copy that.
快
Go!
喔 哥们儿
Whoa, bro!
上啊 小猴子
Go, Monkey Boy!
你们大家 等等我
Guys, wait up!
图克 快点跟上
Tuk! Keep up!
好的 我来了
Okay, okay.
哥们儿 你带她来干嘛？
Bro, why'd you bring her anyway?
她总哭鼻子
She's such a cry baby.
说什么“我要告状”
She's all, "I'm telling.
“你们不能去战场玩”
"You're not supposed to go to the battlefield.
“你不带我 我就告诉妈妈”
"I'll tell Mom if you don't let me come."
你们别欺负她
Don't pick on her.
快来
Come on.
哇 厉害
Oh, sick!
那上面有死人吗？
Are there any dead bodies up there?
哥 来看看 快点
Bro, check it out. Come on.
我去
No shit.
琪莉
Kiri.
Kiri…
琪莉
Kiri.
你还好吗？
Are you okay?
我刚才又昏过去了是不是？
I was doing that thing again, wasn't I?
是啊 昏过去了
Yeah, you were.
- 琪莉 - 琪莉
- Kiri! - Kiri!
琪莉 我们得回去了
Kiri, we have to get back.
走吧
All right, come on.
你怎么了？
What is it?
日蚀之前我们就应该回家的
We're always supposed to be home by eclipse.
这个脚印肯定不是人类的
It's way too big for a human.
- 是阿凡达 - 有可能
- Avatars? - Maybe,
肯定不是我们的人
but they're for sure not ours.
你在做什么
What are you doing?
跟着他
I'm tracking.
小心你的后方
Watch your six.
可以
Clear.
封锁这里
Perimeter up.
该死
Damn.
爸爸肯定不让我们来这儿
We are never supposed to come here.
你要被关禁闭的
Dad is going to ground you.
别说了好不好
Can you stop?
关一辈子
For life.
哥们儿 我们过去看看
Bro, we have got to check this out.
走
Let's go.
哥们儿
Bro,
你爸和我爸在这儿…
that's where your dad and my dad…
打过架
fought.
那是你爸的战斗装甲
That's your dad's actual suit.
天呐 是真的
Holy shit.
莱尔 你去看看
Lyle, see if you can
记录仪上还有什么数据
pull some data off that dash cam.
这东西早就废了
That thing's deader than shit, Colonel.
- 我们也是 - 好吧
- So were we. - All right.
我们得赶紧报告
I gotta call this in.
不行 会惹麻烦的
No, bro, we're gonna get in trouble.
走吧
Let's go.
恶狗 恶狗
Devil Dog, Devil Dog,
我是鹰眼 完毕
this is Eagle Eye, over.
鹰眼 报告你的情况
Eagle Eye. Send your traffic.
我们发现了可疑的人
I got eyes on some guys.
看起来像阿凡达
They look like avatars,
但是都穿着迷彩服带着步枪
but they're in full camo and carrying ARs.
一共有六个人 完毕
There's six of them. Over.
报告位置 完毕
What's your pos? Over.
我们在废弃小屋这儿
We're at the old shack.
谁是我们？
Who's "we"?
我 蜘蛛 琪莉
Me, Spider, Kiri…
还有图克
and Tuk.
儿子 你认真地听我说
Son, you listen to me very carefully.
现在撤退
You pull back right now.
别发出声音
Do not make a sound.
马上离开那儿
You get the hell out of there.
快点 明白吗？
Move! You copy?
是 长官 这就撤
Yes, sir, moving out.
- 你看 我就说了 - 走吧 走
- See, I told you! - Go, go.
爸
Dad,
可以抄近路
I know a quick way!
瞧着吧 你的麻烦大了
You're going to be in so much trouble.
琪莉 闭嘴
Shh! Kiri, stop.
行了 快走
Guys, come on.
日蚀快到了 快点
It's almost eclipse, come on.
图克
Tuk!
放下武器 跪下
Put it down! Down!
放下 我要开枪了
Put it down or I'll shoot you!
跟我来
With me.
快点 放下武器
Drop it! Right now!
都别动 举起手来
Do not move! Put your hands up!
[外星语] 把武器放下 把武器放下
- 跪下 - 蜘蛛
- Hands up! - Spider.
- 跪下 - 抓住他们
- Down! - Get 'em! Get 'em!
- 琪莉 - 过来 过来
- Kiri! - Get over here! Come on!
跪下
Get down!
不许反抗
Stop fighting.
不许动
Don't move!
搜他们的身
Check 'em for weapons!
- 别动 - 琪莉
- Kiri! - Tuk.
[外星语] 冷静…
闭嘴 不许动
Shut up. Don't move.
收获不错呀
What have we here?
别动
Stop.
别伤害他
Pot pung ra'a!
上校
Colonel,
你看
check it out.
人类手指
Four fingers.
是个混血种
We got a half-breed.
什么？
Shit…
把你的手伸出来
Show me your fingers.
你是他的种 对不对？
You're his, aren't you?
你还真挺像他
You're his, all right.
洛阿克 不要
Lo'ak, don't.
不要
Don't!
他在哪儿？
Where is he?
[外星语] 抱歉 我不讲英语…
[外星语] 不跟混蛋讲
[外星语] 你父亲在哪里？
不
No!
怎么
Really?
你是想玩硬的吗？
You wanna play it this way?
你们别伤害他
Pot pung ra'a!
闭嘴
Shut up!
放开他
Pey fpomit sweyn!
琪莉
Kiri!
不 住手
No! Stop!
你们不许碰他
Hey, don't touch her!
拜托 别伤害他
Don't hurt her, please.
别乱动
Don't move.
你叫什么 小子？
What's your name, kid?
蜘蛛
Spider…
索克罗
Socorro.
迈尔斯
Miles?
没有人这么叫我
Nobody calls me that.
真是见鬼了
Well, I'll be damned…
我还以为他们把你送回地球了
Well, I figured they sent you back to Earth.
婴儿进不了冷冻舱 白痴
They can't put babies in cryo, dipshit.
我们怎么办 老大
What are we doin', boss?
蓝军一号呼叫钢穹
Iron Sky, Blue One, Actual.
蓝军一号 报告你的情况
Blue One, Iron Sky, send your traffic.
我们在等待接应 完毕
We are standing by for extract, over.
我们过去
Take us in.
蜻蜓号向左靠近 我们这就去接应
Dragonfly comin' left, we are go for extract.
请注意
Be advised,
我们带回了高价值俘虏
we are bringin' in high value prisoners.
- 放我们走 - 闭嘴
- Let us go! - Shut up.
你们稳住
Sit tight, Blue One,
我们马上赶到
we're inbound to your pos.
预计十分钟
That's bingo in ten.
按时到达
We're on the clock.
- 坐下 - 坐在地上
- Sit! - Come on, in the dirt!
- 休息 - 坐在地上
- Feet up! - Get down on the ground!
莱尔 声音再开大一点
Lyle, get me some audio on this.
- 闭上嘴 - 别看
- Shut your mouth. - Don't look up!
那是萨利的女人
That's Sully's woman.
她是头野兽
She's an animal.
住手 夸里奇
Give it up, Quaritch.
萨利
Sully.
- 战争结束了 - 这个叛徒
- It's all over. - Son of a bitch.
只要我活着就不会结束
Nothin's over while I'm breathin'.
我要的就是这句话
I kinda hoped you'd say that.
安静 安静 安静
Down, down, down.
不 你和伊卡兰留下
No, no, you stay with the ikran.
爸爸
But, Dad…
我和你一样是战士 我应该战斗
I'm a warrior like you. I'm supposed to fight.
奈特亚
Neteyam.
别让我再说第二遍
I'm not gonna say it again.
遵命
Yes, sir.
对 到这儿就结束了
Yeah, there's nothin' after that.
要帮你收回遗体吗？
You want us to recover these remains?
蓝军一号请注意
Blue One, stand by ready.
我们还有三分钟
We are three minutes out.
注意了 还有三分钟
Heads up, three minutes.
注意后方
Watch our six.
闭嘴
Shut up!
给我闭嘴
后方有敌人
Contact rear!
- 后方有敌人 - 琪莉
- Contact rear! - Kiri!
洛阿克
Lo'ak!
糟了
Shit.
- 小崽子 - 洛阿克
- You little shit. - Lo'ak!
- 图克 来 快 - 给我回来
- Tuk, come on. Go, go, go! - Get back here!
快跑
Run!
抓住他们
Grab 'em!
快
Come on!
找掩护 走
Cover! Go!
快走
Come on!
是你吗 萨利夫人？
That you, Mrs. Sully?
别来无恙啊 神射手
I recognize your calling card.
不来见见老朋友吗？
Why don't you come on out, Mrs. Sully?
我们两个之间还有不少账要算呐
You and I, we got some unfinished business.
蜘蛛 来
Spider, come!
恶魔
Demon!
无论杀死你多少次我都奉陪到底
I will kill you as many times as I have to!
我猜你和杰克·萨利一直挺忙的吧
I guess you and the Corporal have been pretty busy, haven't you?
忙着生了一大堆小崽子
Dropped yourself a whole litter of…
混血种
half-breeds.
纳威人
Na'vi!
快走 跑跑跑
Move! Go, go, go!
没事吧 孩子？
You okay? You okay, boy?
没事
Yeah.
好了 好了吗？好了吗？
Okay. With me. Ready? Ready?
好了长官
Yes, sir!
跑
Move!
快点
Come on!
快撤
走走走
Go, go, go!
散开 追杀他们
Flank out. Get after 'em!
蜘蛛
Spider?
Spider!
- 琪莉 - 蜘蛛
- Kiri! - Spider.
快来 快来
Come! Come on.
蜘蛛 他还在下面
Spider. He's down there.
不
No.
长官 我们到了
Ma'am, we're at bingo.
按照约定 十分钟
Ten minutes in enemy airspace.
蓝军一号 回到接应地点 快
Blue One. Get back to the rally point now.
蓝军一号 撤回来
Blue One, fall back.
撤退
Fall back!
撤退 撤退
Fall back, fall back!
往回撤
Move out! Move!
快快快
Move, move, move!
- 琪莉 - 蜘蛛
- Kiri! - Spider!
快来 过来
Come, come.
- 不 - 快
- No. - Come!
走走走 快点 走啊
Go, go, go. Come on. Let's go.
没事 受伤了吗？
Hey, it's okay. You hurt?
- 都没事吧？ - 我没事
- Are you hurt? - No, I'm okay.
- 图克 你呢？ - 别怕
- Tuk, you hurt? - Daddy!
没事
It's okay.
好了 我们安全了 大家都没事吧？
Okay, we're clear. We're clear. Everyone okay?
- 妈妈 - 图克
- Mom! - Tuk.
好了
That's it.
没事了 没事了
It's okay. It's okay. We're okay.
感谢你圣母 谢谢 感谢你
Oh, thank you, Great Mother. Thank you.
谢谢你
Thank you.
蜘蛛在哪儿？
Where's Spider?
他被抓走了
They took him.
被那群人抓走了
好了 别怕亲爱的
Okay. It's all right, baby girl.
他很坚强的
All right? He's a tough kid.
好了
All right.
他会没事的
He's gonna be okay.
我们都会没事的
We're all gonna be okay.
可恶
Goddamn!
拜托
Come on!
放我出去
Let me out of here!
他完全没开化
He's completely feral.
以为自己是纳威人
Thinks he's one of them.
那个家伙 夸里奇
This thing. This Quaritch.
无论他…
Whatever he is…
他怎么了？
What's going on?
他能进到这儿
He can walk right in here.
来到艾娃的鼻子底下
He can walk right under Eywa's nose.
这里是我们的家 我们的家园
This is our family. This is our home.
为了我们的家园
This is about our family.
为了我们的孩子
This is about our little ones.
我做不到 你不能这样做
I cannot. You cannot ask this.
我不能离开我们的族人
I cannot leave my People.
我不愿意
I will not.
他找上我们了
He's hunting us.
他盯上我们一家
He's targeting our family.
你不能这样做
You cannot ask this!
我们的孩子
The children.
一直生活在这里 这片森林
Everything they've ever known. The forest.
我们的家就在这里
This is our home!
他抓了我们的孩子
He had our children.
用刀抵住他们的喉咙
He had 'em under his knife!
这把弓是我父亲临死前亲手交给我的
My father gave me this bow as he lay dying.
他说要保护好族人
And he said protect the People.
你是托鲁克马克多
You're Toruk Makto!
这样可以保护族人
This will protect the People!
夸里奇抓了蜘蛛
Quaritch has Spider.
那孩子什么都知道
And that kid knows everything.
他了解我们的全部底细
He knows our whole operation,
可以带他们到这儿来
and he can lead them right in here.
要是族人把我们藏起来 他们就会丧命
If the People harbor us, they will die.
你不明白吗？
Do you understand?
这太突然了
Look, I got nothing.
我没有计划
I got no plan…
但是我会尽力保护这个家
But I can protect this family.
我能做到
That I can do.
有一件事情不会变
I know one thing.
无论去哪儿
Wherever we go,
我们的家永远是坚实的堡垒
this family is our fortress.
杰克·萨利在哪儿？
Where is Jake Sully?
我不知道
I don't know!
我知道你知道
We know that you know.
我不知道
I don't know!
回忆一下他在哪儿
Just form a picture in your mind.
是不是在悬浮山？
Is it one of the floating mountains?
放我出去
Let me out of here!
他在反抗 再等一会儿
He's fighting us. Give us a minute.
我不知道
I don't know!
你只要有想法 我们就能看到
Just form a thought, and we will see it.
我不知道
I don't know!
听着 我和你一样不喜欢这个
Look, I don't like this any more than you do.
- 他们会藏到哪个部落去？ - 我不知道
- Which clans would be harboring him? - I don't know!
你们杀了我好了
You're gonna have to kill me!
看看这个 能看到他的脑前额叶
Watch this. You're peaking all over the prefrontal.
你不开口我们就会不停地问你
It's not gonna stop until you give us something.
快说他在哪儿？
Where is he?
我都说了我不知道
I don't know, you buttholes! Okay?
我不知道
I don't know!
将军 我试试换种方式来问他
General, let me try the personal angle.
他不是你儿子了
He's not your son.
别太激动了 冷静
Easy, tiger. Easy.
行吗？
We good?
你是块硬骨头
Kid, you got heart.
那些搞科学的用尽手段逼问你
Those science pukes leaned on you pretty hard.
可你什么也没透露
But you gave them nothin'.
我很佩服你
I respect that.
我猜你也许想要这个
I thought you might want this.
迈尔斯·夸里奇上校
That's Colonel Miles Quaritch.
他死了
Deceased.
战斗身亡
Killed in action.
我不是夸里奇
I'm not that man.
可是毕竟我有他的所有记忆
But I do have his memories…
所以我知道
enough to know that, uh,
他肯定不算是个好父亲
well, he wasn't always the best father.
这可不是向你道歉
But that's not an apology.
我不是你爸爸 严格来说
I'm not your father. Technically,
你和我没有任何亲属关系
you and I, we're nothin' to each other.
但是…
But…
我可以帮你
I can help you.
帮助你离开这儿
I can get you outta here.
我不会让你背叛杰克·萨利
I'm not gonna ask you to betray Jake Sully.
我知道你不会的 你很忠诚
I know you'd never do that. You're loyal,
我佩服你的忠诚
and I admire loyalty.
跟我走吧
Just ride along.
不然我只能送你回实验室去了
Otherwise, I gotta give you back to the lab coats.
这是我心上的一块石头
This is like stones in my heart.
塔瑟姆年轻有智慧
Tarsem is wise for his years.
他会成为强大的首领
He will be a strong Olo'eyktan.
旧的首领必须死去
The leader must die.
新的首领才能诞生
So the leader can be born.
托鲁克马克多将要消失
Toruk Makto will disappear.
这样族人就安全了
The People will be safe.
父亲要保护家人
A father protects.
这样他才有意义
It's what gives him meaning.
一个生命结束
One life ends.
另一个生命开始
Another begins.
图克
Tuk.
海洋部落有他们自己的世界
The sea clans are a world unto themselves.
几千个大小岛屿
Thousands of islands.
迷宫一般的群岛
An unknown territory
可以隐没我们的行踪不被敌人发现
into which we could just vanish without a trace.
我们还没到吗？
Are we there yet?
（阿瓦特鲁 梅卡伊纳族村庄）
别带那个
Leave it.
过来
On me.
图克
Tuk.
- 友好一点 - 谁…
- Be nice. - Who…
- 他们是谁呀？ - 友好一点
- Who are they? - Be nice.
不知道他们为何会在这里
We don't know why they are here.
他们来自哪里？
Where did they come from?
冷静 放松点
Easy. Just be cool.
看 那是什么？
Look. What is that?
这东西也算尾巴？
Is that supposed to be a tail?
这也太小了
It's too small.
他们怎么游泳啊？
How are they supposed to swim?
别这样 罗克索 奥农
Do not. Rotxo, Aonung.
特诺瓦里是梅卡伊纳人的首领
Tonowari was the chief of the Metkayina,
他们是岛礁族
the Reef People.
我看见你 特诺瓦里
I See you, Tonowari.
杰克·萨利
Jakesully.
我知道他性格强硬
I knew him as a tough leader.
但我担心的不是特诺瓦里
But it wasn't Tonowari I was worried about.
我看见你 洛纳
I See you, Ronal.
梅卡伊纳大祭司
Tsahik of the Metkayina.
我看见你 洛纳
I See you, Ronal.
你们为什么来这里 杰克·萨利？
Why do you come to us, Jakesully?
我们来寻求庇护
We seek uturu.
庇护？
Uturu?
保护我家人的安全
Yes, sanctuary for my family.
我们属于海洋部落
We are Reef People.
你们是森林部落
You are Forest People.
你们的技能在这没用
Your skills will mean nothing here.
我们可以学习 对吗？
Well, we will learn your ways. Am I right?
是的
Yes.
他们的胳膊太细
Their arms are thin.
- 妈妈 - 他们的尾巴
- Mom. - Their tails…
没有力量
are weak.
在水里游泳 速度很慢
You will be slow in the water.
- 这些孩子甚至不算是纳威人吧？ - 爸爸
- These children are not even true Na'vi. - Dad.
我们是纳威人
Yes, we are!
他们有恶魔的血
They have demon blood!
看呢 看
Look. Look.
我本来是天空人
Look, I was born of the Sky People,
但现在我成了纳威人 可以适应的
and now I am Na'vi. All right? You can adapt.
我们会适应的
We will adapt.
好吗？
Okay?
我丈夫曾经是托鲁克马克多
My husband was Toruk Makto.
他带领部落取得了胜利…
He led the clans to victory…
打败了天空人
against the Sky People.
你们这是胜利的样子？
This you call victory?
跑来这里求助陌生人
Hiding among strangers?
看来艾娃已经不再眷顾你了
It seems Eywa has turned her back on you,
命运之子
Chosen One.
我替我的妻子道歉 她…
I apologize for my mate. She's…
- 你用不着替我道歉 - 她一路飞行了很远
- Do not apologize for me. - flown a long way,
- 她有些累了 - 杰克
- and she's exhausted. - Jake.
托鲁克马克多是伟大的战争英雄
Toruk Makto is a great war leader.
纳威人都知道他的故事
All Na'vi people know his story.
梅卡伊纳现在…
But we Metkayina…
- 爸爸 - 没有战争
- Dad. - are not at war.
我们绝不会让你把战争带到这里来
We cannot let you bring your war here.
我不打仗了
I'm done with war.
好吗
Okay?
我只是想保证家人的安全
I just want to keep my family safe.
我们请求你们的庇护
Uturu has been asked.
我们要被赶走吗？
Do we have to go?
会没事的
We'll be okay.
托鲁克马克多和他的家人可以留在这里
Toruk Makto and his family will stay with us.
要像对待兄弟姐妹一样对他们
Treat them as our brothers and sisters.
他们还不了解海洋
Now, they do not know the sea.
他们现在就像婴儿一样
So they will be like babies
第一次睁开眼睛
taking their first breath.
我们要教他们学习水之道
Teach them our ways,
让他们不至于对自己毫无用处
so they do not suffer the shame of being
感到惭愧
useless.
应该说什么？
Okay, what do we say?
谢谢
Thank you.
- 谢谢 - 谢谢
- Thank you. - Thank you.
谢谢你们
Thank you.
我儿子奥农 我女儿喜芮亚
My son, Aonung, our daughter, Tsireya,
负责教你们的孩子
will show your children what to do.
- 爸爸 为什么… - 就这样定了
- Father, why do… - It is decided.
来吧 我带你们去村子看看
Come. I will show you our village.
这边走
This way.
图克 走吧
Tuk, let's go.
在上面
Just up here.
不 不
No, no.
这边是你们的
This is for you.
你们的新家
Your new home.
哎 这不错
Yeah, this will work.
很漂亮
This is great.
很棒对吗？
It's nice, right?
萨利家 集合
Okay, Sullys, fall in.
记得吗？ 开家庭会议
Remember? Family meeting.
好了 都坐下 动起来
Come on. Take a knee. Let's go.
琪莉
Kiri.
干嘛？
What?
听好
Okay.
这几天你们几个要表现得好一点
I need you kids on your best behavior.
我是认真的
I mean it.
学快点 多干活
Learn fast. Pull your weight.
别惹麻烦
Don't cause trouble.
明白吗？
You got it?
遵命
Yes, sir.
我想回家
I want to go home.
图克
Oh, Tuk.
Tuk,
这里就是家
this is our home now.
我们要挺过这一关
Now we're gonna get through this.
只要互相支持 一定可以挺过去
We're gonna get through this if we have each other's backs.
好吗？
All right?
爸爸平时都怎么说的？
What does your father always say?
一家人不能分开
Sullys stick together.
没错 一家人不能分开
That's right. Sullys stick together.
再说得有力量一点
Now this time with some feeling.
来
Yeah.
一家人不能分开
Sullys stick together.
快来
Come on.
[外星语] 和我们一起游泳吧
[外星语] 他们怎么回事？
[外星语] 那些家伙不会潜水
[外星语] 别这样
[外星语] 他们还在学习
你们还好吗？
Are you all right?
你们游得太快了
You're too fast!
等等我们
Wait for us.
调整呼吸
Just breathe.
放松
Breathe.
你们潜水不行
You are not good divers.
你们在树上倒还行 可是…
Maybe good at swinging through trees, but…
这不公平
Come on, bro.
我们看不懂你们用的手语
We don't speak this finger talk, guys.
不懂你们说什么
We don't know what you're saying.
我会教你们的
I will teach you.
- 琪莉在哪儿？ - 琪莉
- Where is Kiri? - Kiri?
- 谁？ - 琪莉
- Who? - Kiri.
她去哪儿了？
Where is Kiri?
看到她了吗？
Did you see her?
你跟他们上去
Get on the ship,
乖乖坐着 不要碍别人事
find a seat, and keep out of the way.
准备运输
Ready for transport!
出发
Let's go!
麻利点
Chop-chop.
这个好
Sweet.
等一下 小机灵鬼
Hold on there, hotshot!
给我听好了
You listen up.
你戴的面罩里装了追踪器
There's a tracker built in that mask.
落地之后你要是敢逃跑
We hit the ground, and you take off,
我两分钟就能把你抓回来
I'll have you back in two minutes,
然后我就要好好抽你一顿
and I will give you a old-school ass-whippin'.
听明白了吗？
Understood?
是 长官
Yes, sir.
好了吗？
We up?
集结完毕
Team's up.
你们都听好
All right, listen up.
杰克·萨利已经跑了
Jake Sully's gone to ground.
没关系
Don't matter.
我们总能找到他
Wherever he is, we'll find him,
还能顺便找到他那个疯老婆
and his batshit crazy wife, too.
为此
To do so,
我们要变成纳威人
we go Na'vi.
从头到脚都要变
Full tilt, all the way.
就是说像纳威人一样进食
That means we eat Na'vi.
像纳威人一样骑行
We ride Na'vi.
像纳威人一样思考
Think Na'vi.
[外星语] 而且要开始说纳威人的语言
[外星语] 你这样也叫说纳威话吗？
[外星语] 你听起来就像是三岁小孩！
大学问家呀
All right, smart guy.
从现在起你从吉祥物小猴子升为官方翻译
You just went from bein' our monkey mascot to official interpreter.
这是伊鲁
These are ilu.
想在这儿活下去
If you want to live here,
就得骑他们
you have to ride.
慢慢建立连接
Make the bond gently.
感受它的呼吸
Feel his breath.
感受它的力量
Feel his strength.
抓住这里
Hold here.
看他的腿
Look at his legs.
抓紧了
Hold on.
你还好吗 森林小子？
You all right, Forest Boy?
这是战士的坐骑
This is a warrior's mount.
不容易驾驭
Not easy to master.
也许你应该
Perhaps you should
先学会骑伊鲁
start with an ilu.
不 就这个
Nah. This one.
你要记住
Now remember,
潜入水下时找好位置
when you dive back in, good position.
这非常重要
Very important.
我可以的
I got this.
来吧
Come on.
保持这样 好吗？
That's it, okay.
稳住
Steady.
该死
Ah, shit.
我好喜欢它
I love her already.
吸气
Breathe in.
然后呼气
And breathe out.
想象用气息扰动火焰
Imagine flickering a flame.
让心跳逐渐变得舒缓
You must slow down your heartbeat.
吸气
Breathe in.
从腹部这里呼吸
Breathe from down here.
慢慢呼气
Breathe out slowly.
洛阿克 你的心跳很快
Lo'ak, your heartbeat is fast.
- 抱歉 - 集中精神
- Sorry. - Try to focus.
- 好的 - 吸气
- Okay. - Breathe in.
呼气
And breathe out.
排除所有杂念
Let your mind go clear.
这才是正确的呼吸
You are learning to breathe.
快点 没吃饭是吧？
Come on! Keep up, losers!
让我试试
I got this.
笑什么？
What?
纳威小孩不用武器就能驯服伊卡兰
Na'vi kids younger than me do this with their bare hands.
杰克·萨利也没用武器？
Jake Sully did it the hard way?
你觉得呢？
What do you think?
我们该怎么做 上校？
What are we doin', Colonel?
这下有好戏看了
This is gonna be good.
好吧 跟上
All right, move up.
咱们俩玩玩吧
It's you and me, cupcake.
我是不是忘说了要先把它的嘴绑上？
Did I mention you're supposed to tie the mouth shut first?
谢了 小子
Thanks a lot, kid!
跟上跟上
Move up, move up!
你看见了？
You see 'em?
好了 去别的地方看看
All right, let's go. We're Oscar Mike.
走吧
Come on.
快点 我们走
Let's go. We're outta here.
看
Yeah!
我做到了
That's right!
好啊 上校 太棒了
Yeah, Colonel! Get some!
好啊 上校
Yeah, Colonel!
下一个谁来？
Who's up next?
水之道无穷无尽 无始无终
The way of water has no beginning and no end.
海洋包围着你
The sea is around you
充盈着你
and in you.
海洋是你的家
The sea is your home
它见证你到来
before your birth
也目送你归去
and after your death.
我们的心脏在世界的子宫中跳动
Our hearts beat in the womb of the world.
我们的呼吸在黑暗的深海中灼烧
Our breath burns in the shadows of the deep.
海洋给予一切
The sea gives
也剥夺一切
and the sea takes.
水连接世间万物
Water connects all things.
从生到死
Life to death.
从黑暗
Darkness
到光明
to light.
我做到了
I got it!
- 喜芮亚 - 你成功了
- Tsireya! - You did it!
[外星语] 用它可以在水下呼吸
她看什么呢？
What is she doing?
谁知道？
I don't know.
她干嘛盯着沙子看？
She's just looking at the sand.
你说什么？
What'd you say?
请问你是不是…
Are you some kind of…
怪胎？
freak?
他问你是不是怪胎
He asked if you are a freak.
不是
No.
你确定吗？
Are you sure?
你长得都不像纳威人
I mean, you're not even real Na'vi.
看看你的手
Look at these hands.
怎么多一根手指…
I mean, look at them…
一边儿去 臭鱼
Back off, fishlips!
又一个手指畸形的怪胎
Oh, another four-fingered freak.
你们看 他那根小尾巴
Look at his little baby tail!
- 别碰我 - 小尾巴
- Don't touch me! - Aw, baby tail!
离我们远点
Leave us alone!
他不正常
He's not normal.
- 看他的尾巴 - 可怜的小尾巴
- Look at his tail. - Aw, baby tail!
太可爱了
It is so cute!
你们没听见吗？
You heard what she said.
离他们远一点
Leave them alone.
啊 是大哥哥来…
Ah, big brother come…
滚开
Back off.
马上
Now.
这就对了
Smart choice.
从现在起
And from now on,
对我妹妹放尊重一点
I need you to respect my sister.
我们走
Let's go.
拜拜
Bye-bye!
看看他们
Look at them.
全是畸形
They're all freaks.
一家子怪胎
The whole family.
- 洛阿克 - 我跟他们说
- Lo'ak. - I got this, bro.
我的手确实很怪
I know this hand is funny.
没错 我是怪胎 外星人
Look, I'm a freak. An alien.
但我的手也很有用
But it can do something really cool.
你们看
Watch.
它可以紧紧握住 像这样
First, I ball it up real tight like this.
对吗？然后…
Okay? Then…
看好了 这叫拳头
It's called a punch, bitch!
以后不许再欺负我姐姐
Don't ever touch my sister again.
奥农 揍他
Aonung! Show him!
来啊
Come here!
停下
Stop this!
别打了
Stop it!
这样太蠢了
So stupid!
我的尾巴
Ow, my tail!
我的耳朵 放开
My ear! Let go!
他抓住我的耳朵了
He's got my ear!
我怎么跟你们说的 还记得吗？
What was the one thing I asked? The one thing!
- 不要惹麻烦 - 不要惹麻烦
- Stay out of trouble. - Stay out of trouble.
- 对 - 都是我的错
- Right. - It was my fault.
不是你的错
I don't think so.
你别替他背黑锅 你这个蠢货
You gotta stop takin' the heat for this knucklehead.
不 爸爸 奥农欺负琪莉
Look, Dad. Aonung was picking on Kiri.
管她叫怪胎
He called her a freak.
你去向奥农道歉
Go apologize to Aonung.
什么？
What?
他是首领的儿子 你明白吗？
He is the chief's son. Do you understand?
不管怎么样 你去和他和好
I don't care how you do it. Just go make peace.
快去
Just go.
你们赢了还是输了
So what'd the other guys look like?
赢了
Worse.
那就好
That's good.
他们可惨了
A lot worse.
滚出去
Get outta here.
发生什么事了？
What is wrong?
没事 我很好
Nothing. I'm fine.
我没有什么不好的
Why should I not be fine?
为什么我不能像其他人一样
Why can't I just be like everyone else?
琪莉
Kiri.
森林小子在这干什么？
What's tree boy doing here?
对不起我打了你
I'm sorry I hit you.
还把你打得那么惨
So many times.
交个朋友吧
We should be friends.
我们去打猎
Come hunting with us.
去礁石外面
Outside the reef.
大人打猎的地方
It's where the men hunt.
不行 我爸爸不让去
No way. I'm not allowed.
我问错人了 应该问你哥哥
I must be asking the wrong brother.
那走吧
Let's do it.
来呀 快来
Come on! Come on!
跟上 森林小子
Keep up, Forest Boy!
（三兄弟岩）
嘿 你还活着
Hey, you lived!
这一趟太刺激了
That was insane, cuz!
这边
This way.
带你去个好地方
I know a good spot.
[外星语] 召唤鱼群
[外星语] 真是个笨蛋！
你们人呢？
Hey, guys!
奥农
Aonung!
出来吧 别闹了
Come on, this isn't funny!
奥农
Hey, Aonung!
怎么回事？
Holy shit.
你是图鲲
You're a tulkun.
你救了我的命
You saved my life.
谢谢你
Thank you.
谢谢
朋友 你说什么我不懂
Buddy, I have no idea what you just said.
他们把你弄伤了
They hurt you, didn't they?
我帮你拔出来
I'll try to pull it out.
相信我 好吗？
Just trust me, okay?
朋友
Friends?
没错 我们是朋友
That's right, we're friends.
朋友
Friends.
哥们
Bro!
[外星语] 我很抱歉
你怎么了 小丫头？
So, what is it, baby girl?
想蜘蛛了？
You missin' Spider?
- 是啊 - 是啊
- Yeah. - Yeah?
我不是为这个哭
But that's not it.
好
Okay…
那是为什么呢？
So what is it?
我能感觉到的
I feel her, Dad.
感觉到谁？
You feel who?
艾娃
Eywa.
我听到她的呼吸
I hear her breathing.
听到她的心跳
I hear her heartbeat.
她离我那么近
She's so close.
她却在在那儿…
She's just there…
像一句要说出口的话
like a word about to be spoken.
你一定觉得我已经疯了
I know you think I'm crazy.
你没有疯 好孩子
You're not crazy, baby girl.
艾娃的心跳是什么样的？
So what does Eywa's heartbeat sound like?
很有力
Mighty.
你再对他说一遍
Tell him what you told me!
你喜欢看星星？
You like lookin' at the stars?
我爸爸就是从星星上来的
You know, my dad came from a star.
那一颗
That one.
在那儿
Right there.
洛阿克
Lo'ak!
噢 这下可惨了
Oh, man. I'm in trouble.
快走 我们以后再见
Go. I will see you again.
- 孩子回来了 - 萨利家的
- The boy has returned! - It is the Sully boy.
- 他回来了 - 回来了
- They found the boy. - They found him.
已经回来了
They found the boy.
让我看看你 好吧
Let's have a look at you. Okay.
他没事 没事
He's fine. He's fine,
- 对 只有一点擦伤 - 洛阿克
- yeah. Just a few scratches. - Lo'ak!
你再敢乱跑
I pray for the strength that…
看我不把你的两只眼睛挖出来
I will not pluck the eyeballs out of my youngest son!
不
No.
我儿子很清楚不应该带他去那里
My son knows better than to take him outside the reef.
这件事怪他
The blame is his.
好吧 我们走
Okay, let's go.
不
No.
这不是奥农的错
This is not Aonung's fault.
是我的主意
This was my idea.
奥农还劝我别去
Aonung tried to talk me out of it.
真的
Really.
走吧
Come on.
洛阿克
Lo'ak.
对不起
I'm sorry.
走啊
Come on.
有我呐
I got this.
这是真的吗？
Is this true?
奥农 你在想什么？
Aonung. What were you thinking?
爸爸 你说过要和他们做朋友
Dad, you told me to make friends with these kids.
- 我只是想和他们一起… - 我不想听
- That's all I was trying to… - I don't want to hear it.
爸爸
Dad…
你让我们都跟着你丢人
You brought shame to this family.
我能走了吗？
Can I go now?
再惹麻烦我就把你尾巴剁了
Any more trouble, I jerk a knot in your tail.
听见了吗？
You read me?
是 长官 听见了
Yes, sir. Lima Charlie.
走吧
Go on.
你当时在哪儿？
Where were you?
对啊
Yeah.
你怎么不看着点你弟弟？
What happened to "keep an eye on your brother"?
抱歉 长官
Sorry, sir.
你为什么帮我说话？
Why did you speak for me?
因为我很清楚父母对你失望是什么感觉
Because I know what it's like to be one big disappointment.
我真想亲眼看看
I wish I'd been there.
这次经历是大海送你的礼物
The ocean blessed you with a gift, brother.
但是图鲲今年还没有洄游
The tulkun have not returned yet.
而且他们从来不单独行动
And anyway, no tulkun is ever alone.
因为他落单了
Well, this one was.
它身上少了一只鳍
He had a missing fin.
左边的鳍断掉了
Like a stump. On the left side.
真可怜
Poor tulkun.
帕亚坎
Payakan.
- 什么？ - 是帕亚坎
- What? - It's Payakan.
帕亚坎是谁？
Who's Payakan?
一只年轻的图鲲
A young bull who went rogue.
他被同伴赶出来了
He's outcast. Alone.
还断了一只鳍
And he has a missing fin.
都说帕亚坎会杀人
They say he is a killer.
- 不 不 - 他杀了纳威人
- No, no. - He killed Na'vi,
它还杀别的图鲲
and other tulkun.
不是在这 在很远的南边
Not here, but far to the south.
- 不 它不会这样 - 洛阿克
- No, he's no killer. - Lo'ak,
你能活下来就很幸运了
you are lucky to be alive.
你们听我说
I'm telling you guys.
它救了我的命
He saved my life.
它是朋友
He's my friend.
好弟弟
My baby bro!
勇敢的小战士
The Mighty Warrior
你遇到杀人图鲲
who faced the killer tulkun,
还平安回来了
and lived to tell about it, huh?
你们根本没听
You guys aren't listening.
洛阿克 我听了
Lo'ak, I'm listening.
洛阿克回来
Lo'ak, come back.
都怪你们
You skxawngs.
帕亚坎
Payakan!
见到你真好
It's good to see you.
你怎么被赶出来了
Why are you outcast?
怎么了？
What happened?
[外星语] 太痛苦了
我相信你
I trust you.
你可以相信我
You can trust me.
这也太恶心了
Bro, that's disgusting!
[外星语] 游快点！
我们到了
We are here.
我们管这里叫仙祖湾
This is the Cove of the Ancestors.
是我们最神圣的地方
Our most sacred place.
日蚀之前这里的景色是最美的
Eclipse is the best time of day to be here.
就是这儿
This is it.
这就是灵魂树
This is the Spirit Tree.
我美丽的女儿
My beautiful daughter.
嘿 妈妈
Hi, Ma.
见到你 我太高兴了
I'm so happy to see you.
你好像有心事？
But you look troubled.
我的好孩子
My sweet girl.
会好起来的
It will be okay.
怎么了 宝贝？
What is it, baby?
为什么我和别人不一样？
Why am I different?
圣母艾娃到底想告诉我什么？
What does the Great Mother want from me?
我父亲到底是谁？
Who was my father?
我的女儿
Oh, my darling.
不
No!
- 快点 - 琪莉
- Come on. - Kiri!
琪莉
Kiri!
琪莉怎么了？出什么事了？
What is wrong? What is it?
是癫痫发作
It was a seizure.
她有呼吸吗？
Is she breathing?
有呼吸吗？
带她回村里去 快点
Get her to the village! Hurry!
回去 快点
Let's go! Let's move!
图克 来
Tuk, come.
见到你真好
It's good to see you.
拿设备 奈特亚
Let's get the gear. Neteyam!
奈特亚 让他们别过来
Neteyam, keep them back!
她怎么样？
How is she?
她现在还昏迷着
She's still unconscious.
没有出血
There's no bleed.
也没有骨折
There's no fracture.
没有缺氧的迹象
No effects of hypoxia.
大脑没问题
The brain looks good.
可现在她的前额叶仍然有癫痫发作时候的放电现象
But we still have this interictal activity right here in the prefrontal.
- 好 - 她确实癫痫发作了
- Okay. - She's definitely had a seizure.
应该可以排除是中毒
I think we can rule out toxins.
等等 那是什么
So what is it?
还不知道
Until this point…
看来我不需要待在这里
I see that I am not needed here.
等等 你是大祭司
You are Tsahik!
把这些东西拿走
Remove these things.
出去 这些都没用
Out! You have done nothing!
走吧 走吧 我们休息一下
Come on, come on. Let's just take a break.
等等 我把静脉针取了
Okay, hold on. I gotta take her IV off.
她说自己能够感受到艾娃
She said that she can feel Eywa.
能听到她的心跳
She can hear her heartbeat.
- 是的 - 什么？
- That's it. - What?
这就是典型的前额叶癫痫症状
That is classic frontal lobe epilepsy.
- 癫痫？ - 对
- Epilepsy? - Yep.
会看到幻想 还会…
You see visions. You get…
幻想神明在对自己说话 像她现在这样
states of religious ecstasy like the kind she's describing.
她这次发病的原因是意识连接灵魂树导致的
Pluggin' into the Spirit Tree is some sort of a trigger.
以后绝对不能再让她这么干了
You definitely can't let her do that anymore.
不会吧？
What? Ever?
杰克
Jake.
下次她在水里发作癫痫
If she seizes underwater again,
可能就会丧命
it could kill her.
琪莉
Kiri!
你醒了
You're awake!
琪莉
Oh, Kiri.
我的好孩子
Kiri, my sweet child.
我的好女儿
Oh, my sweet little girl.
说这句
Okay, this one.
我看见你
"I See you."
纳阿提 纳阿提
Ngaati. Ngaati!
我就是这么说的
That's what I just said, isn't it?
不是纳提 是纳阿提
Not "Naati. Ngaati."
纳阿提 纳阿提
Ngaati, ngaati.
懂了 像从鼻子里擤出来的
All right. Like comin' out your nose or something.
老大
Boss,
远程侦察队发现雷达信号
long-range patrol picked up a radar hit.
一架武装直升机
A rogue gunship.
在哪儿？
Where?
东海 向北四百公里
Eastern sea. Four hundred klicks north.
坐稳了
Hang on.
那个信号时断时续
The signal was intermittent,
进入开阔水域就消失了 但是…
and they lost it over open water but…
从它的方向来看
if you project the track,
它的目的地是这片群岛
it hits this island group.
那边有几百个岛屿呢
That's hundreds of islands.
还有那么多村子 太难找了
That's a big search box with lots of villages.
他肯定在这儿
This is our guy.
只要你给我船只和飞机
You give me ships and aircraft,
我就能抓他回来
I'll bring you back his scalp.
不明物体靠近
Bogies inbound.
船长
Skipper.
- 都停下 - 都停下
- All stop. - All stop.
都停下
All stop. Aye.
你是索克斯比？
You Scoresby?
听说有个混蛋要征用我的船 是你吗？
Are you the asshole who's commandeering my ship?
对 就是
That would be me.
我们这次的目标是这一片群岛
The target's pretty much this whole island group.
我从来没去过
Never been up there.
你了解这里 博士 都有哪些土著？
You know those waters, doc. What kinda indigenous we got?
主要是梅卡伊那人
Metkayina, mostly.
还有坦努伊人 大概五十个村子
Some Ta'unui. Maybe fifty villages.
请问你是谁？
And you are who?
我是伊安·加文
I'm Ian Garvin.
海洋生物学家
Marine biologist.
五十个村子也好
Fifty villages.
一百个也好 都无所谓 全搜一遍
A hundred villages. I don't care. We'll search 'em all.
我是图鲲猎人
I hunt tulkun.
这艘船是捕猎船 船员都是猎人
That's what I'm rigged for. That's all my guys do.
我们要完成指标
I've got quotas to meet.
我这礼貌是装的
I'll be nice once.
你别当真
Then I won't.
好吧 既然没得选
Well, if you can't get out of it,
那就干吧
get into it!
- 所有船员就位 - 哎 别碰
- All crews to stations! - Hey, don't touch.
准备起飞 飞行速度
Helm, bring her up. Flight speed.
飞行速度 是
Flight speed, aye.
那是什么？
What was that?
- 它们来了 - 怎么了
- They're coming! - What's going on?
是图鲲回来了
The tulkun have returned!
大家听着 我们的兄弟姐妹回来了
Everybody, our Brothers and Sisters have returned.
每年图鲲都会迁徙
In their endless cycle of migration,
现在它们回家了
the tulkun had come home.
我看到你了
I See you!
琪莉
Kiri!
琪莉 你来看 来呀
Kiri, come on. Come on!
图克 别来烦我
Tuk, leave me alone.
- 快来呀 - 干嘛？
- Come on! - What?
到底怎么了？
What do you want?
看 你看
Look. Look.
来呀
Come on.
我们去看看
Let's go meet them.
看
Look,
是我的心灵姐妹
it's my Spirit Sister.
[外星语] 姐姐 我看见你
[外星语] 我看见你 妹妹 我很高兴
[外星语] 你的儿子很漂亮
[外星语] 谢谢 你的孩子怎么样了？
[外星语] 我的孩子很强壮
[外星语] 我遇见一个男孩
他们会分享故事
It was a time for stories.
讲述分开的时光
Of their season apart.
死亡 新生
Of deaths and births.
老朋友 新爱人
Of old friends and new loves.
（坦努伊村）
孩子们
Children.
冷静一下
Be calm,
族人们
my people.
我们要找武器 通讯设备
We're looking for weapons, comms.
任何科技装备
Any kind of tech.
跪下
Get down.
你也是 你看到了吧？
You too. You see this?
跪下
Get down.
跪下 闭嘴
Stay down and shut up!
[外星语] 这个人…
[外星语] 我们知道他就在这些岛屿里面
[外星语] 在这里吗？这个村子吗？
[外星语] 我们完全是不同的氏族…
[外星语] 影像中的这个人…
[外星语] 来自森林
他们在说什么？
Now what's he saying?
说没看到他
They never saw him.
他们是海洋部落
These are Sea People.
没有森林里的人
Forest People don't come here.
我可不信这一套
I ain't buyin' that.
[外星语] 他应该离开这里…
[外星语] 到森林里去找那个人
他们一无所知
They don't know anything.
毙了那畜牲
Shoot that animal.
你这是干什么？
What the hell are you doing?
跪下
Down!
[外星语] 冷静
嘿 你现在听懂了吗？
Hey, your ears workin' now?
[外星语] 冷静！冷静！
见识到它的厉害了吧
You see what these can do, huh?
杰克·萨利
Jake Sully.
托鲁克马克多
Toruk Makto!
[外星语] 他已经说了他什么都不知道！
- 干掉她 - 跪下
- Put her down! - Get down!
跪下
Get down!
住手
Stop!
那你现在去和他说清楚
You make it real clear to him.
不交出杰克·萨利
He doesn't give up Sully,
我就杀了大祭司
we kill the Tsahik.
不 我才不去说
No, I'm not doin' that.
真的吗？
Is that right?
我才不要干这种事
I'm not gonna be a part of this!
跪下
Get down!
这些人什么都不知道
These people don't know anything!
他们没有骗你
They don't know anything!
- 不许动 - 跪下
- Don't move! - Stay down.
闭嘴
Shut up!
要不要干掉她？
We really gonna waste her?
求你了 求你别这么做
Please. Please don't do this.
这样不对
This is wrong.
你们这样做不对
What you're doing here is wrong.
求你了
Please.
把村子烧了
Burn the hooches.
哎 点火吧
Hey, light 'em up.
点火 都烧了
Light 'em up. All of 'em!
- 用喷火器 - 点火
- Flamethrowers up! - Light 'em up.
[外星语] 对不起！
[外星语] 我不知道会这样！
[外星语] 让他们住手！
对不起
I'm sorry.
我们要走了
We're outta here.
你别碰我
Don't touch me!
对不起
I'm sorry.
我们走
Let's go.
- 准备出发 - 好吧 我们走
- Saddle up. - All right. Let's go.
怎么了？
What's wrong?
是天空人
Sky People.
他们一直在找你
They're looking for you, Jakesully.
在南边
South.
带着一个会说纳威语的人类男孩
They have a human boy who speaks Na'vi.
他们杀人了吗？
Did they kill anybody?
暂时没有
Not yet.
只是威胁
They threaten.
你放心 我们的人不会透露你在哪儿
But the villagers will not tell them where you are.
我下了命令
By my order.
我们一定要找到这个恶魔
We must hunt this demon.
困住他
Trap him.
杀了他
Kill him.
我们要小心行事
We've gotta be smart.
要聪明些
We gotta be smart.
如果攻击夸里奇 就会暴露我们的位置
If we hit Quaritch, they're gonna know where we are,
他们就会倾其所有大举进攻这里
and they're gonna come here with everything they've got.
那我们要怎么做？
Then what is our plan?
那是托鲁克马克多
That's Toruk Makto!
把头低下
Head down.
来过这儿吗？
Has he been here?
这样问没用的
This shit ain't workin'.
对 他们在耍我们
Nah, they're stonewallin' us.
我们追得太紧
If we turn up the heat,
杰克只会继续跑
he's just gonna keep runnin'.
得逼他出来
We gotta draw him out.
我不干了
I'm over it.
我还要完成指标呢
I've got quotas to meet.
你想打猎吗？
You wanna hunt?
我答应你
Let's hunt.
- 走吧 - 在这儿？不行
- Come on. - Here? Not here.
人太多了
There's too many villages.
不 这样不行
No. No, no, no.
恕我直言
Respectfully, sir, uh,
你还不理解图鲲和海洋部落
you do not understand the kinship bonds
纳威人之间的深切联系
between the tulkun and the ocean Na'vi.
杀死图鲲就像杀害他们的家人一样
It would be like murdering a member of their family.
要是在这杀图鲲
If we start hunting here,
没多久 敌人就会找上门来
the hostiles will come after us.
正是这样
Exactly.
我就想见见其中一个
One hostile in particular.
我知道你的感受
I know how you feel.
有时候我也很孤独
I feel all alone too.
告诉我
Tell me.
你为什么被赶走？
Why are you outcast?
对不起
I'm sorry.
真对不起
I'm so sorry.
没事
It's okay.
都是你造成的
You allowed this.
你看着他和那个图鲲建立心灵纽带
You allowed him to bond with the outcast!
喜芮亚
Tsireya.
你真是让我太失望了
You disappoint me, daughter.
你呢？
And you,
你是英雄的儿子
son of a great warrior,
应该明白事理才对
who has been taught better.
帕亚坎救了我的命
Payakan saved my life, sir.
您不了解他
You don't know him.
别再说了
No, Lo'ak.
坐下
Sit.
都坐下
Sit down!
你们认真听我说
Hear my words, boy.
在初始之歌的年代
In the days of the First Songs,
图鲲彼此之间一直在争斗
tulkun fought amongst themselves,
为了领地
for territory,
为了复仇
and for revenge.
它们逐渐意识到
But they came to believe…
杀戮 无论其理由多么正义
that killing, no matter how justified,
只会带来更多的杀戮
only brings more killing.
于是 所有杀戮被禁止
So all killing was forbidden.
这就是图鲲的规矩
This is the Tulkun Way.
帕亚坎
Payakan.
杀害了同伴
is a killer,
所以…
so,
它被驱逐了
he is outcast.
抱歉 首领
I'm sorry, sir.
- 您说得不对 - 洛阿克
- But you're wrong. - Lo'ak.
你是在对首领说话吗？
You speak to Olo'eyktan!
- 我知道我… - 够了
- I know what I… - That's enough!
我没有说谎
I know what I know.
别再说了
That's enough.
我来教训他
I'll deal with this one.
暴风雨会过去的
This storm will pass.
洛阿克
Lo'ak,
我今天已经看到了
I saw something today.
一个森林男孩被图鲲选中
I saw a Forest Boy chosen by tulkun.
我从心底为你骄傲
I am very proud of you.
帕亚坎没有杀同伴
Payakan didn't kill those boys.
我看到了
I saw it all.
恶魔船当着它的面杀了它妈妈
The demon ship killed his mother right in front of him.
它召集年轻图鲲和岛礁人去进攻恶魔船
He gathered the young bulls and the reef boys together to attack the ship.
他们都被杀死了
And they were all killed,
凶手是天空人不是帕亚坎
but by the Sky People. Not by him.
- 它没有杀戮 - 不 洛阿克
- He's not a killer. - No, Lo'ak.
图鲲认为这就是杀戮
By the Tulkun Way, he is.
它要对同伴负责
He bears those deaths.
它要用一辈子来赎罪吗？
Does he have to pay for it for the rest of his life?
它知道自己错了
He knows what he did was wrong.
绝不会再犯了
He would never do it again.
我们得告诉我父亲…
We must tell my father…
不 不
No. No.
我和我爸之间的麻烦已经够多了
I'm in enough trouble with my dad already.
你父亲会理解的
Your father will understand this.
他不会的
No, he won't.
他什么也不明白
He doesn't understand anything.
整个部落都讨厌我
The whole clan hates me.
恶魔血统
Demon blood.
外星人 他们只看到这些
Alien. That's all they see.
我看见你
I See you.
你是图鲲的兄弟了
You are Brother of Tulkun.
你是我们的一员
You are one of us now.
找到母的啦？
You got my mother?
还带着小的 信号很强 范围四千
Mother and calf. Strong signal. Range 4, 000.
把它弄到船上来
Bring it down, on the hull.
即将降落
Comin' down, aye.
放下水翼
Foils deployed.
潜水小队 两分钟后
Sub teams, two minutes!
开始下水
Let's get in there!
关闭舱门
Hatches closed!
快 赶紧 快点儿
Come on, hustle! Hustle!
船员各就各位 两分钟
Crews to their boats. Two minutes.
我们去赚一票大的
Let's make some bank.
战船小队
Boat crews!
解开固定装置 都解开
Let's get those tie downs off! Tie downs off!
所有船下水 都下水
All boats in! Boats in!
我们出发
Let's go, baby!
继续前进
We're rollin'!
深水炸弹准备进攻
Stand by depth charges,
开火 开火 开火
and fire, fire, fire!
那是什么？
What's that?
他们在干嘛？
What are they doin'?
那是回声定位传感器
Those are echolocation sensors.
图鲲认路用的
How they navigate.
必须要举到水面上
They have to hold them out of the water,
不然它们就聋了
or they'll go deaf.
猎人们
Picadors!
快上 去呀
Get in there! Go on.
冲啊 给我上
Get in there. Get up in there!
为了让那头雌性图鲲落单
They're gonna cut the cow from the rest of the pod…
他们会用声波炮
using the sound cannon.
目标是图鲲妈妈 因为幼崽游得慢
They target the mother because the calf swims slowly,
它不会抛弃幼崽
and she won't leave the calf.
它们不会反抗吗？
Do they ever fight back?
不会 它们完全不会碰你
Nah, never seen 'em lift a fin.
不过皮很厚 不好杀
Tough bastards to kill though.
潜水小队 出发
Sub teams, go!
准备释放
And release.
Release, release.
目标来了
There's our gal.
发现目标
Target in sight.
3-6号 准备鱼叉
3-6 is in hot with harpoons.
准备攻击
Here we go, baby.
我们从下方攻击
See, we go in from below
图鲲的腹部比较脆弱
where there's gaps in the armor.
好了 上吧 靠近它
All right, let's go. Get up in there.
正在靠近
I'm goin' in.
再近一点
Get me in close.
跟紧了
Hold her steady.
进入射程 一发炮弹
In range. Arm one.
装填 锁定目标
Arming, target lock.
准备 发射
And one away.
两号准备
Two's in hot.
- 一发炮弹 - 装填
- Arm one. - Arming.
开火
Fire.
- 干得好 再来一发 - 装填
- Good strike. Arm two. - Arming.
发射
Two away.
打中了
Booyah!
漂亮
Nice.
3-6号 请我们喝酒啊
3-6, you owe us a beer.
那些气囊能给它减速
You see, the bags slow her down
- 强制它浮在水面上 - 是啊
- and keep her up at the surface. - Yeah.
到它上面
Get on her!
送我过去
Get me in there.
直接落在它身上
Straight up on her.
还有三十米
30 meters.
鱼叉上带了炸药
Explosive-tipped harpoon.
还有十米 送我过去 落到指定部位
Ten meters. Get me in there. Put me in the pocket.
好 稳一点
Now steady, steady.
保持射程
Stay with her.
稳住 稳住
Hold. Hold.
线拉直了
Line's runnin'!
站稳扶好啊 上校
Hold on to your ponytail, Colonel!
全力向后拉
Hold back full!
向后拉
Back full, aye.
拉住了
Hold her.
爆炸鱼叉直接射进了它的胸口
She takes an explosive harpoon to the chest,
它居然还在跑
and she's still runnin'.
太漂亮了
Beautiful.
要取图鲲的腺体只能从下面走
The only way to reach the gland is from below.
往上钻 穿透硬颚
We drill up through the hard palate
直到大脑 然后…
into the brain. And…
他们是具有高度智慧的生物
These are highly intelligent beings.
很可能比我们都聪明
Probably smarter than us.
那比我呢？
Not smarter than me.
拿你比水平也太低了
That is setting the bar very low.
可是我有鱼叉
Hey, I'm the one with the harpoon.
是啊
Yep.
你怎么知道图鲲比我们聪明？
How do you know? That they're smarter than us?
他们有更多的神经元和通路
More neurons, more pathways.
他们不光比我们聪明
Not only are they smarter,
还感情丰富
they're deeply emotional.
更有灵性
More spiritual.
看这个区域
See, this region here…
对应着人类的情绪中枢
corresponds with our emotional centers,
但他的占比比人类要大得多
but proportionally it's much larger.
图鲲有音乐
They have music,
有哲学
philosophy,
有数学
mathematics,
有复杂的语言
complex language.
好了
Okay.
提取到了
Here we go.
这可就是钱呐
Show me the money.
费那么大劲就为了这个？
So that's what this is all about?
就是它
That's it.
不老精髓
Amrita.
这些图鲲也是倒霉
Bad luck for the big guys.
它们脑袋里的分泌物能停止人类衰老
This stuff just happens to stop human aging. Like…
完全停止
stops it.
一丁点不老精髓都是受无数人追捧的稀世珍宝
Ounce for ounce the single most valuable substance known to man.
这么一小管就能卖个…
This little vial here is worth like,
八千万
80 million.
接住
Think fast!
请你别这样
Please don't.
这样不好笑
It's never funny.
正因为有不老精髓 我们才有设备和资金在潘多拉活动
Amrita is what's paying for everything here on Pandora now.
包括你做研究 我说的对吗 博士？
Even your research. Ain't that right, Dr. G?
所以我酗酒
It's why I drink.
只拿这些？
That's all you take?
那别的 就不要了？
I mean, you just waste the rest?
取掉气囊
Drop the bags.
让它沉下去
Let's sink her!
不 留下气囊
No. Leave the bags.
让他们知道是谁干的
I want 'em to know it was us.
用我的船做诱饵是要单收费的
I charge extra for bein' used as bait.
它的名字叫洛瓦
Her name is Ro'a.
洛瓦是我的心灵姐妹
She was my Spirit Sister.
她创造了那么多动听的歌
She was a composer of songs.
备受尊敬
Much revered.
我们一起唱歌
We would sing together.
它等了好几个繁殖周期才生下这个孩子
She waited many breeding cycles to have this calf.
整个部落都为它高兴
The clan were so happy for her.
可这算什么呢 特诺瓦里？
What is this, Tonowari?
这算什么？
What is this?
我的心灵姐妹…
My Spirit Sister…
和它的孩子…
and her baby…
都被天空人残忍地杀害了
have been murdered by the Sky People!
战火已经烧到了我们的家
This war has come to us.
我们知道天空人一直在捕猎图鲲
We knew about this hunting of our tulkun people.
但从前他们在地平线外
But it was over the horizon,
非常远
far away.
现在 他们来这儿了
Now it is here!
不 别这样
No, you don't…
你们得理解天空人的思维方式
You gotta understand how the Sky People think.
他们根本不在乎生态平衡
They don't care about the Great Balance.
不用管天空人怎么想
We don't answer to Sky People!
听着 都听他说
Listen. Listen to him.
天空人是不会停手的
The Sky People are not gonna stop.
这只是开始
This is only the beginning.
你们要告诉图鲲 让它们离开
You gotta tell your tulkun to leave.
告诉它们 走得越远越好
You gotta tell them to go far away!
离开？
Leave?
你和我们一起生活
You live among us,
可是你什么也没有学会
and you learn nothing!
我们要战斗 要保护我们的兄弟姐妹
We will fight to protect our brothers and sisters!
不不不
No, no, no.
如果你们反抗
If you attack,
如果你们进攻
if you fight,
他们会毁了你们
then they will destroy you!
他们会毁掉你们爱的一切
They will destroy everything that you love.
不
No!
- 听我说 - 不要战斗 不要战斗
- You hear my words! - We will fight! We will fight!
听我说
Hear my words!
都冷静
Stay calm.
冷静些
Stay calm!
听我父亲说完
Listen to my father.
见鬼
Damn it!
他说的是实话
He speaks the truth.
你们告诉图鲲
You tell the tulkun
一旦被这个打中
that if they're hit by one of these,
就会被天空人追踪
they're marked for death.
我可以去拆掉追踪器
And call for me, I'll silence it.
让图鲲活着才是最重要的
Saving their lives, that's all that matters.
对吗？
Right?
解救你们的家人
Saving your family.
告诉图鲲
Tell the tulkun.
去
Go.
快去
Go!
我们必须反抗
We must fight.
亲爱的
MaJake.
我绝不会再袖手旁观了
I will not stand and do nothing!
这是陷阱 反抗就中计了
It's a trap. They want us to hit back.
他们抓的不是图鲲
They're not hunting tulkun.
而是我们
They're hunting us.
你可不能乱跑 好弟弟
No way you're rolling out of here, baby brother.
我得去提醒帕亚坎
I have to warn Payakan about the pingers.
不行
No.
你待在这里 哪儿也不许去
You've gotta keep your skxawng ass here.
它被赶出来了
He's outcast.
除了我没人能提醒它
There's nobody to warn him but me.
弟弟
Bro,
为什么你总是让事情变复杂
why do you always have to make things so hard?
不
No.
你是想问为什么我不像你一样完美？
You mean why can't I be the perfect son like you?
做个完美的小战士
The perfect little soldier.
因为我不是你
Well, I'm not you!
好吗？
Okay?
我不是你
I'm not you.
它是我兄弟
He's my brother.
我要去
I'm going.
噢 它是你兄弟？
Oh, he's your brother?
不 我才是你兄弟
No, I'm your brother.
洛阿克
Lo'ak!
放开我
Get off me.
洛阿克
Lo'ak!
- 回来 - 快走
- Come back! - Come on.
他要去找帕亚坎
He's going to Payakan.
快回来
Come back!
那是洛阿克 洛阿克
There's Lo'ak! Lo'ak.
洛阿克
Lo'ak!
洛阿克要去找帕亚坎
Lo'ak's going to find Payakan!
等一等
Wait up!
先别走
Hold on!
所有船员就位
All crews to stations.
好了 各位 开工赚钱了
All right, people. Come on. Let's make some money!
帕亚坎
Payakan!
兄弟
Brother!
洛阿克
Lo'ak!
等等
Wait!
怎么了 出什么事了？
What is it? What's wrong?
糟了
Shit!
冷静 别慌
Stay calm. Stay calm.
我来帮你
I got this.
该死
Shit!
洛阿克
Lo'ak!
哥 快来帮我一把
Bro, come on! Help me out!
快 船要来了
Hurry, the ship's coming!
就在那儿
They're over there!
快一点
Bro, come on!
快拉
Bro.
- 快来帮忙 - 快点
- Come on, bro. - Hurry!
去报告
Call it in!
告诉爸爸
Call Dad!
去告诉他 快 快去
Call Dad! Just go! Do it!
- 快去啊 - 洛阿克 快 快呀
- Just do it. - Lo'ak, go! Hurry!
爸爸 不是 恶狗 能听到吗？
Dad. I mean, Devil Dog. Do you read me?
你看到他们去哪儿了吗？
Did you see where they went?
我是鹰眼 是否收到
It's Eagle Eye, do you copy?
- 他们去礁石外面 - 嘿 洛阿克
- They went outside the reef. - Yeah, Lo'ak.
爸爸
Dad!
有一头图鲲受到了攻击
We're with a tulkun that's under attack.
捕猎船就要来了
Killer ship's inbound.
还有两公里
It's about two klicks out.
你身边有谁？
Who's with you?
我们全都在 奥农和提蕾娅也在
It's all of us. Aonung and Tsireya too.
我们都在三兄岩
We're at Three Brothers Rocks.
你们去找掩护 不要交战
You get to cover, and you do not engage.
懂吗 听到了吗？
All right? You hear me?
不要动 我们这就来
Do not engage. We're comin'.
是 长官
Yes, sir.
船越来越近了
It's getting closer!
- 三 二 拉 - 拉
- Three, two, pull! - Pull!
孩子们有危险
Kids are under attack!
孩子们有危险 他们在保护图鲲
The kids are under attack. They were defending a tulkun.
你的孩子也在
It's your kids too.
是恶魔船？
The demon ship?
对 我们快走
Yes! We gotta go!
拿武器 发警报
Weapons. Sound the alarm!
你应该留下来
You should stay back.
我就要去
I ride!
走
Come!
潜水小队 关闭舱门
Sub teams, hatches close.
两分钟后出发
Two-minute warning.
奥农
Aonung!
快点 加油
Hurry up! Come on!
兄弟 快点
Bro, hurry up!
快点 快
Go, go, go!
拉呀 快
Pull! Now!
- 所有人一起用力 - 拉
- Everybody! Together! - Pull!
这下可好了
I'll be damned.
杰克的小崽子
Sully's kids.
我们走 你留下
Let's roll. Not you.
出发
Saddle up.
范围大概七百米
Range is 700 meters.
追踪信号很清楚
Pinger signal is good.
快拉 用力
Pull, harder!
用力
Pull!
使劲拉
Pull, harder!
快
Go!
出来了 琪莉 出来了
It's out! Kiri, it's out!
- 走 图克 快走 - 大家快走
- Go. Tuk, go. - Go, everybody!
快点 离开这
Come on. Get out of here!
走那儿边 我来引开他们
Go that way! I'll draw them off.
- 好 - 洛阿克 快来
- Okay. - Lo'ak, come.
帕亚坎
Payakan.
快走 下去
Go, go, dive!
快 下水
Now, dive!
抓紧了
Grab on.
范围三百米
Range 300.
深水炸弹 准备发射
Ready depth charges,
开火 开火 开火
and fire, fire, fire.
不要用深水炸弹
No depth charges.
索克斯比 听到没有
Scoresby, you copy?
那些孩子死了就没价值了
These kids are worthless to me dead.
都停火
Hold your fire.
围成一圈儿 把他们困在中间
Circle out. Get a cordon around 'em.
潜水艇都下去
Get your subs in the water.
潜水小队下水
Sub teams, get wet.
螃蟹去右侧 包抄他们
Crabs flank right. Get around on 'em.
别跟丢了 保持距离
Don't lose 'em. Stay on 'em now.
收起两翼 要进去了
Planes up. We're goin' in!
好 搞定了
Oh, hell yeah!
锁定目标 发射
Tone on lock. Two away.
图克在哪儿？
Where is Tuk?
你看见了吗？
Did you see her?
图克
Tuk!
发现目标
Target in sight.
他要来了
It is coming.
我们走
We gotta go!
- 换渔网 - 收到
- Switch net. - Switching.
发射
Fire.
撑住
Hold on!
放我出去
Let me out!
- 当心 - 图克 快逃
- Watch out! - Tuk, move!
拿开手 拿开手
Move your hand! Move your hand!
- 割断它 - 快 快呀
- Cut it! - Hurry, hurry!
哎 给我回来
Hey, kid, get back here!
放下武器
Drop the weapon.
- 放下武器 - 快放下 放下
- Put the weapon down! - Put it down. Put it down!
放下
Stay down.
抓住他 抓住他
Get him! Get him!
放下武器
Put the weapon down!
快扔掉
Drop it, now!
- 放下 - 把刀子扔掉
- Put it down! - Drop the knife.
扔掉
Drop it.
你干什么？住手
Wat are you doing? Stop!
住手 别伤害他们
Stop. Don't hurt them.
不许动
Stop moving.
- 蜘蛛 - 兄弟 你还好吗？
- Spider! - Bro, you okay?
好 我很好
Yeah. Great, cuz.
- 好得很 - 好了
- Never better. - Down!
你闭嘴
Shut your mouth.
别反抗了 别动
Knock it off. Stay still.
闭嘴 安静点儿
Shut up. Quiet.
带他回驾驶舱
Get back to the bridge.
别让他出来
Keep him there!
我自己会走
I'm going, I'm going.
好啊
Yeah.
我记得你
I remember you.
把他们拷起来 都拷上
Cuff 'em to the rail. All of 'em.
快点
Let's go.
- 快点 走 - 过来
- Let's go. Move! - Over here.
小心点 他们会咬人
Watch 'em. They bite.
老实跪下 好了
Get on your knees. On 'em.
把手给我
Give me your hand.
不
No!
- 另一只 - 不要
- Now the other. - No.
勇敢点
Be brave.
纳威人来了
Na'vi inbound!
- 散开 武器准备 - 爸爸
- Spread out. Weapons up. - Dad!
往左边 都散开
Push left. Spread out.
停下 让他们停
Stop. Stop them.
是萨利
It's Sully.
二百七十米
300 yards.
孩子们被抓了
They got our kids.
你女儿
Your daughter.
图克 洛阿克
Tuk. Lo'ak.
杰克 让你的朋友们都退下
Jake, tell your friends to stand down.
想要回孩子
You want your kids back,
你就单独过来
you come out alone.
你知道我可没有多少耐心
You know better than to test my resolve.
洛阿克 不
Lo'ak! No!
妈的
Fuck!
杰克 我本来很关照你
I took you under my wing, Jake.
可你背叛了我
You betrayed me.
你杀了同类
You killed your own.
无辜的男人和女人
Good men. Good women.
我会毫不犹豫地对你的孩子动手
I will not hesitate to execute your kid.
你等一下
Just wait one.
先别动
Hold here.
这些人类杀害了图鲲
They are killers of tulkun.
要让他们偿命
They must die.
这里
Here.
现在
Today.
他们要的是我
It's me that they want.
做这些都是为了找我
That's what all this has been about, all right?
猎杀图鲲也是 绑架孩子们也是
The hunting of our tulkun. The taking of our kids.
是你带来的灾祸
You brought this upon us!
是你
You!
所以我要去了结这一切
Well, then it's me that has to do this.
我可没有那么多耐心
Offer's fixin' to expire.
决定好了吗？
What's it gonna be?
收起武器
Check your fire.
我这就过来
I'm comin' out.
亲爱的 发生了什么？
MaJake, what is happening?
杰克？
MaJake?
提高警惕 武器就位
Stay tense, everybody. All weapons.
可以打中他
Easy shot.
开枪会激怒他们
You hit him now, they attack.
等他上船再说
Wait till he's on board.
帕亚坎
Payakan!
不
No!
图克
Tuk!
开火 开火
Open fire. Open fire!
兄弟
Brother!
- 快转向 - 转向
- Come about! - Comin' about!
送我过去
Get me around!
让我射击
Get me a shot!
快 快
Go, go!
小心
Look out!
送我过去
Get me around!
快快快快
Go, go, go, go!
送我过去
Get in there,
到射程之内 快快快
get me in range. Go, go, go.
卧倒
Down!
我的妈呀
Bloody hell!
快点开火 快开火
Open fire! Open fire!
杰克过来了
Sully's inbound.
从上面盯住
I want eyes on!
好吧 我们走 准备升空
All right, let's go. Saddle up. We're up!
所有人都给我开火
Somebody shoot something!
停下
Stop!
糟了
Oh, shit!
去追他们 快
Get after them. Go!
进水了 戴面罩
Breach! Masks on!
氧气罩 快点
Masks on! Go!
换一个镜头
Switching feeds.
怎么样？看到什么了？
What have we got? What are we lookin' at?
抓住他
Get this guy!
快拉开他
Get him out of here!
冷静
Calm down!
快拉 快拉
Pull! Pull!
快快快
Go, go, go!
报告受损情况
Damage report!
二号和三号舱进水严重
Flooding. Compartment two and three.
你还好吗
You okay?
左后方
Port bow!
左转弯 给我开火
Hard port! Open fire!
要打中它
Get me a shot!
别跑
Got ya!
赶快断开
Cut us away!
没有反应
Not responding!
快点把钢索切断
Get us off the cable!
看看现在谁有鱼叉
Who's got the harpoon now?
全速后退
Back full!
装弹
Reload!
不要钢索了 别管他了
Not the cable, you idiot!
船体不行了
We're dead in the water.
进水了 上抽水泵
Taking on water. Pumps on.
准备开火
Man your weapons!
你不是认为自己比别的种族聪明吗？
I thought you were the intelligent species here, Scoresby.
闭上你那张臭嘴 加文
Shut ya cakehole, Garvin.
你在哪儿呢？
Where are you?
狡猾的家伙
Cheeky bugger.
你以为自己很聪明是吧？
You think you're pretty clever, don't ya?
快趴下
Get down!
水泵坏了
Pumps aren't working.
弃船吧 弃船逃生
Abandon ship! Abandon ship!
- 带他去救生艇 - 是 长官
- Get him to a boat! - Yes, sir.
所有人快走 带上面罩
Let's go, people! Let's move! Mask up!
奈特亚
Neteyam!
好弟弟
Hey, baby brother.
要帮忙吗？
Need some help?
别废话 快点 给我们松开
Shut up. Come on. Get us loose.
好了 带图克走
Okay, get Tuk out of here.
哥 你快点
Bro, hurry up!
好 来了
Okay. Come on.
谁是勇敢小战士啊？来说啊
Who's the Mighty Warrior? Come on. Say it.
- 哥 - 好了 走吧
- Bro! - Come on. Let's go.
洛阿克
Lo'ak!
蜘蛛被抓了
They've got Spider.
我们得去救他 来吧
We've gotta get him. Come on.
来吧 哥
Come on, bro.
总不能丢下他
We can't leave him.
放我走
Let me go!
不
No!
看呀
Look!
起来吧 小宝贝
Let's go, buttercup. Get up.
我才不是小宝贝 变态
I'm not your buttercup, perv!
我们得回去救出琪莉
We've got to go back for her.
图克 等等
Tuk, wait!
一家人不能分开
Sullys stick together.
我们走 准备降落 开始
All right, we're a go for drop. Let's go.
都给我等一下 等等 好了
Wait right there, guys. Wait. All right.
可以降落
Clear to drop!
检查氧气罩 都带紧了
Check your mask. Make sure it's tight.
别碰我
I'm good, dumbass.
快点走
Move, move!
疏散人员 快点 撤
Evacuating, people. Come on. Let's go.
图克 这样做很危险
Tuk, this is not a good idea.
图克
Tuk!
琪莉
Kiri.
图克
Tuk!
快点 从这儿切
Cut it here.
快点
Come on.
不 不
No!
我看着她
I got her.
我们还有机会呢
We can still get this done.
当然
Hell yeah.
我怎么又被绑起来了
I can't believe I'm tied up again!
走快一点
Hurry up, guys.
你想跟船一起沉吗？
You want to go down with this ship?
- 哥们儿 快 - 我们走
- Bro, come on. - Let's go.
谢谢你们
Thanks, guys.
- 走 - 不
- Go! - No!
- 快走 快 - 走走走
- Bro, come on! - Go, go, go!
走走走
Go, go, go!
枪给我
Give me that!
快走 走
Go, go, go!
这边儿
This way.
掩护掩护
Cover, cover!
看到了吧
You see 'em?
哥们
Bro!
- 刚才太惊险了 - 是啊
- That was insane, cuz. - Yeah.
快上来
Get on!
快来呀
Come on, bro!
傻小子
You skxawng.
我中枪了
I'm shot.
糟了
Shit!
来帮我
Gimme a hand!
- 抬他起来 - 没问题
- Keep him up! - I got him.
走
Come on.
- 抓好 - 我抓稳了
- Grab him. - Bro, I got him.
这下糟了
Holy shit.
拉他上去
Hold him up!
振作点儿
Bro, come on.
没事 兄弟 有我在
It's okay, bro. I got you.
快点 快快快
Hurry. Go, go, go!
琪莉和图克被抓了
They have Kiri and Tuk.
不能回去
I can't go back.
爸爸
Dad!
爸爸 救人 是奈特亚
Dad, help! It's Neteyam!
快
Hurry!
快接住他
Here! Take him.
- 哦 不 - 奈特亚 他受伤了
- Oh, no. - It's Neteyam! He's hurt!
- 杰克 - 来 来
- Jake. - Come on. Come on!
你快救他
Hurry, please!
拉
Pull!
哥们 他的头 他的头
Bro, watch his head. Watch his head.
拉
Pull!
上来
Come on!
当心他的头
Just watch his head.
好了
Okay.
没事了 哥
It's okay, bro.
你安全了
We got you.
噢 不
Oh, no.
摁住伤口
Put pressure.
Put pressure on it.
爸爸 我…
Dad, I…
没事的 我在
It's okay. I'm here.
- 不不不不不 - 没事的 我在
- No, no, no, no, no. - It's okay. I'm here.
- 没事的 儿子 有我 - 不
- It's okay, son. I gotcha. - No…
没事的
It's okay.
我想回家
I want to go home.
我知道 我知道
I know. I know.
没事的 我们回家
It's okay, we're goin' home.
我们回家
We're goin' home.
没事的 没事的
It's okay. It's okay.
爸爸 我…
Dad, I…
奈特亚
Neteyam…
不不不不
No. No, no, no.
奈特亚
Neteyam!
Neteyam.
圣母艾娃
Oh, Great Mother.
不要这样 圣母艾娃
No, Great Mother.
求你了
Please.
我的儿子
Oh, my son.
好儿子
My son.
不
No!
我的孩子
My son!
不
No!
能听到吗 萨利下士？
Can you hear me, Corporal?
不不不
No, no, no.
对 你应该能听到
Yeah, yeah, I think you can.
你的女儿在这
I got your daughters.
条件和之前一样
Same deal as before.
你来换他们
You for them.
不
No!
你姐妹们在哪儿？
Where are your sisters?
你姐妹们 都在哪儿？
Your sisters. Where are they?
不知道
I don't know.
- 她们在哪儿？ - 她们在船上
- Where are they? - They're on the ship.
被抓到了那艘船上
They're tied up on the ship.
她们… 她们在船的中部
They're… They're at the moon pool.
放潜水艇的地方 出口旁边
At… At the well deck. Midships.
什么？
What?
走吧 我指给你
Come on. I'll show you.
跟我来
Come on.
- 我带路 - 回我话 下士
- I'll show you. - Talk to me, Corporal.
- 你 上去 - 麻烦你拿出点诚意
- Z, up top. - I need somethin', Jake,
不然后果自负
or there's gonna be consequences.
好 听见了
Yeah, I hear you.
- 来吧 - 快来
- Come on. - Come on!
走了 我们得走了
Let's go. We gotta go.
快点走
Come on, let's go.
- 不 - 走吧
- No! - Let's go.
- 听着 听着 听我说 - 不
- Listen. Listen. Listen to me. - No…
听我说
Listen to me.
听我说 听我说 我们的女儿被抓了
Listen to me. Listen to me. They have our daughters.
我们的女儿被抓了
They have our daughters.
我需要你和我一起
I need you with me.
我需要你振作起来
And I need you to be strong.
要挺住
Right now.
冷静一点
Strong heart.
你要坚强起来
嗯
Yeah.
我们去救女儿
Let's go get our daughters.
你陪着你哥哥
You stay with your brother.
爸爸 我也想一起去
Dad, I want to go with you.
你做的够多了
You've done enough.
爸爸
Dad…
先停火
Hold fire.
我们走
Let's go.
他来了
He's coming.
没问题 走 走
I'm good. Go, go!
一定要抓住他
Let's get this guy.
我们就是为了这个来的
It's what we came here for.
你陪着他
Stay with him.
不
No…
警觉点 注意观察四周
Heads on a swivel, guys.
走
Go.
她们在哪儿？
Where are they?
中部甲板 放潜水艇的地方
The middle deck. Where they launch the subs.
中间有个井口
There's, like, a pool in the center.
她们在栏杆旁边
They're at the forward railing.
你留在这里
No, no. Stay here.
考虑得怎么样？
Talk to me, Corporal.
船要沉了
This ship's going down
你女儿也要完了
and your girls with it.
你儿子本来不用死
Your boy didn't have to die.
这都是你自找的
You brought that on yourself.
你以为能保护家人安全
You thought you could keep your family safe,
可你做不到
but you can't.
只有一个办法让他们安全
Only one way to keep them safe.
做个了结吧 不然你会再少一个孩子
So let's get this over with before you lose another kid.
趴下
Get down!
谁受伤了？
Who's down?
- 那个老狗在吗？ - 报数
- Zdinarsik, you copy? - Sound off!
安全
Clear!
普拉格 能听到吗？
Prager. You read?
上面 上面
Eyes up. Eyes up!
追击
Move up!
向左边 去
Push left. Go!
你去右边 包抄
Push right. Get around on her.
谁看到目标了？
Who's got eyes?
追
Move!
杰克
MaJake.
是妈妈
It's Mom!
你等着吧
That's right.
他们就要来找你了
They're coming for you.
爸爸 爸爸
Dad! Dad.
你姐姐在哪儿？
Okay. Where's your sister?
琪莉在哪儿？
Where is she? Where is she?
那边儿 在那边儿
That way. That way.
好 你跟着我
Okay, stay behind me.
琪莉
Kiri!
快没时间了 下士
Runnin' out of time here, Corporal.
你失去了一个孩子
You already lost one kid today.
难道还想失去第二个吗？
You really wanna lose another?
别挑战我的耐心
Do not test me!
爸爸 杀了他
Just kill him, Dad!
琪莉
Kiri.
放下你的武器
Weapons down.
不要 别听他的
Don't. Don't do it.
放下
Down!
踢远一点
Kick 'em away.
快点
Do it!
不
No.
把自己铐上
Cuff yourself.
不 不 别伤害她 好吗？
No! No, don't hurt her, okay?
- 不要 - 不许过来
- Don't… - Stand there!
- 不要 - 别动
- Don't! - Don't move!
一步也不行
Not a step.
铐上 马上
Cuffs on. Now.
你这个人渣
You son of a bitch.
求你了 别伤害她
Please, don't hurt her.
放了她
Release.
否则我就动手
Or I cut.
你真以为我在乎那个孩子
What, you think I care about some kid?
他不是我的
He's not mine.
我们甚至不算同一个物种
We're not even the same species.
不要 求你了 别…
Just please don't…
别伤害她
don't hurt her.
拜托你了 放她走
Just please let her go.
- 求你了 - 不要
- Don't. - Please!
- 不要杀他 - 听我说
- Don't kill him. - Listen to me!
放她走 别伤害她
Let her go. Don't hurt her.
妈妈 你别杀他
Mom, don't kill him.
用你儿子换我儿子
A son for a son.
求你了 别伤害她
Please don't hurt her.
我动手了
I cut.
拜托你放她走好吗？
Please just let her go, okay?
放了琪莉
Just let her go.
不
No!
琪莉 琪莉 琪莉
Kiri… Kiri. Kiri.
蜘蛛
Spider.
蜘蛛 快带他们走
Spider, get 'em out of here.
快
Come on.
我们走 图克
Guys. Tuk.
你欠我一条命
I owe you a death.
妈妈
Mom.
- 妈妈 - 来吧
- Mama. - Come.
走吧
Come on.
求你了 妈妈
Please, Mama.
你不会走吧 杰克？
You're not leaving, are you, Jake?
- 没事的 - 你知道我还活着
- It's okay. - Knowin' I'm out there.
你知道我不会住手
Knowin' that I'll never stop.
我会来找你
I'm coming for you.
等我找到你 我就会杀光你们全家
And when I do, I'll kill your whole family.
爸爸…
Dad…
该结束了
Then let's get it done.
杰克
Jake!
- 烧过来了 - 回去 回去
- It's coming! - Back. Back.
回到船上去 快
Get back to the ship. Go!
图克 快游 快游
Tuk, swim, swim.
- 跟上 - 跟紧
- Stay close. - Come on.
- 继续游 快点 - 跟上
- Keep moving. Go, go, go! - Stay close.
图克 图克
Tuk. Tuk.
图克
Tuk!
- 抓住她 - 妈妈 抓住我的手
- Grab her! - Mom, take my hand!
- 稳住 - 稳住
- Hold on! - Hold on!
图克
Tuk!
妈妈
Mom!
不
No!
- 琪莉 快来 琪莉 - 不
- Kiri, come on. Kiri… - No…
- 我们得赶快离开 快来啊 - 不
- we've got to go, come on. - No!
图克
Tuk!
走 快点 爬上来
Go! Climb. Climb!
请你快点
Kiri, come on!
我们快走
Come on, let's go!
- 妈妈 - 快点 快游
- Mom! - Swim! Swim.
快走 图克
Go, Tuk.
爬上去
Climb up.
- 妈妈 - 快点
- Mom… - Run!
快
Go!
快快快
Go, go, go!
继续爬 快
Keep climbing! Go!
我帮你
I got you.
把手给我 快上来
Give me your hand! Come on!
好了 图克
Okay… Tuk!
救我
Open it!
退后 退后
Move back. Move back.
快来
Come.
图克
Tuk!
快爬
Climb!
快
Come on.
快爬
Climb!
上去
Go!
快上去
Go up!
船要翻了
We're rolling over!
- 快快快快 - 好的
- Go, go, go, go! - Okay…
不
No!
- 妈妈 - 图克
- Mom! - Tuk.
琪莉
Kiri!
快走
Keep going!
这边这边
This way, this way!
好
Okay.
走
Go!
打开 快打开
Open it! Open it!
妈妈
Mom!
快
Come on!
走 图克
Go, Tuk!
我们出不去了
There's no way out!
你要跟紧我
Stay together, okay?
- 好的 - 跟紧了
- Yes. - Stay together.
好的
Yes.
圣母艾娃
Oh, Great Mother!
圣母艾娃 救救我们
Oh, Great Mother, help us!
琪莉
Kiri!
哥们儿
Bro!
爸爸妈妈还在下面
Mom and Dad are down there.
- 在船上 - 抓住
- In the ship. - Grab on.
哥们 可以走了
Bro, I'm good. Go!
好
Okay.
杰克
Jake!
爸爸
Dad.
妈的
Fuck!
混蛋 坚持住
Come on, you son of a bitch!
爸爸 呼吸
Dad, just breathe.
奈特亚
Neteyam?
不 我是洛阿克
No, Dad. It's Lo'ak.
洛阿克
Oh, Lo'ak.
对不起
I'm sorry, sir.
奈特亚不在了 都是我的错
I'm sorry about Neteyam. It's all my fault.
别傻了
Just focus.
想办法逃出去
Focus on now.
空气快没了
We're losing the air pocket.
快点 我们要赶快
Come on. We've gotta move.
快点 爸爸
Come on, Dad.
你知道路吗？
You know your way out?
知道 我知道 但要憋很长一口气才行
I think so. But, Dad, it's gonna be a long breath-hold.
我撑不过去了
I can't make it.
- 你可以 你可以 - 不
- You can. You can. - No.
- 你现在就走 - 不
- So you gotta go right now. - No.
我不能再失去你 爸爸
I can't lose you too, Dad.
求你了
Please.
妈妈 我害怕
Mama, I'm scared.
不要怕
It is all right.
你跟紧我
Stay close to me.
跟紧妈妈
Stay close to Mama.
你知道
It's okay.
让心跳变得舒缓
You just have to slow your heart down.
放松下来
Be real calm.
从这里呼吸
Breathe from here.
从这里
Hey, breathe from here.
水之道无穷无尽 无始无终
The way of water has no beginning and no end.
海洋包围着你充盈着你
The sea is around you and in you.
海洋是你的家
The sea is your home
它见证你到来 也目送你归去
before your birth and after your death.
海洋给予一切 也剥夺一切
The sea gives and the sea takes.
水连结世间万物
Water connects all things.
从生到死
Life to death.
从黑暗到光明
Darkness to light.
琪莉
Kiri!
Kiri.
一切都会好起来的 小妹妹
Everything's going to be all right, little sister.
妈妈
Mom,
我要给你带上这个
I'm gonna give this to you.
它会帮助你
It'll help you.
爸爸 你能做到吗？
Dad, you can do this.
- 相信我 - 是的
- Trust me. - Yeah.
心神平静
Calm your heart.
深呼吸
Big breaths.
吸一口气
Last breath.
跟我来
Follow me.
坚持住
Hold on.
保持呼吸
Just breathe.
深呼吸
谢谢你
Thank you.
我看见你
I See you,
儿子
son.
杰克
MaJake!
- 爸爸 - 妈妈
- Dad! - Mom!
爸爸 爸爸
Dad. Dad.
过来
Come on.
- 过来 - 图克
- Come here. - Tuk.
- 安全了 - 给
- I got you. - Here.
哥哥
Brother.
一家人不能分开
Sullys stick together.
这是我们最大的弱点…
It was our greatest weakness…
也是最强的力量
and our great strength.
谢谢你 圣母艾娃
Thank you, Great Mother.
谢谢
Thank you.
我们走吧
Let's move out.
儿子
Son.
跟我走吧
Come with me.
蜘蛛
Spider!
小猴子
Monkey Boy!
蜘蛛
Spider.
- 还好吗？ - 还好
- You all right? - Yeah.
过来
Come here.
用你儿子换我儿子
A son for a son.
乐珠总会数到最后一个
Every songcord must have a last bead.
父亲要保护家人
A father protects.
这样他才有意义
It's what gives him meaning.
纳威人说能量都是借来的
The People say that all energy is only borrowed.
终有一天要还回去
And one day you have to give it back.
艾娃 她心中放着所有的儿女
Eywa holds all her children in her heart.
记得所有的故事
Nothing is ever lost.
奈特亚
Neteyam!
我们家
My family and I,
明天就要搬走了
we'll move on tomorrow.
去很远的地方
Far away from here.
你儿子和我们的祖先在一起
Your son lies with our ancestors.
你们也是梅卡伊纳人了
You are Metkayina now.
于是就这样
And there it was.
我们加入了海洋部落
We are Sea People now.
这里是我们的家了
This is our home.
爸爸
Dad!
你看我捉到了什么？
Look what I caught!
这条鱼可真大
Oh, that's a big one.
它在水池里
He was in that pool.
在石头后面
By the rocks.
和你说的一样
Right where you said.
怎么了 爸爸？
What is it, Dad?
你怎么哭了？
Why are you crying?
我见到你太高兴了 孩子
I'm just happy to see you, boy.
见到你我也很高兴
I'm happy to see you, too.
给 你试试
Here. You try.
好啊
Okay.
这还有鱼吗
Leave any for me?
嗯 可能有
Uh, maybe.
我射中了 看
Yeah! Check that out. See?
现在我明白了
I see now.
逃亡不能让我的家人安全
I can't save my family by running.
这里是我们的家
This is our home.
是我们的堡垒
This is our fortress.
这里就是我们守护的地方
This is where we make our stand.
《阿凡达2：水之道》
∮ 我以为我可以保护好你 不为了我而赎罪 ∮
∮ I thought I could protect you from paying for my sins ∮
∮ 我已经在这片土地上行走了足够长的时间 ∮
∮ And I been walking this earth long enough that death's a gift ∮
∮ 哦 姑娘 ∮
∮ Oh, girl ∮
∮ 在这世上隐忍的生活 ∮
∮ Been living this life so patient ∮
∮ 直到再次遇见你 这就是我们所面对的 ∮
∮ Until I see you again, it's war we're facing ∮
∮ 我知道如果我注定一死 我唯一的选择仍是捍卫 ∮
∮ I know that if I die, my only choice is still defending ∮
∮ 无论旁人说什么 ∮
∮ No matter what they say ∮
∮ 我对你的爱胜过那些天兵天将的力量 ∮
∮ My love for you is greater than their powers and their armies from above ∮
∮ 你赐予了我力量 ∮
∮ You give me strength ∮
∮ 无论怎样我与你同在 ∮
∮ I'm with you either way ∮
∮ 假如我死了 假如我留在这里 请赐予我力量 ∮
∮ If I die, if I stay, give me strength ∮
∮ 无论怎样我与你同在 ∮
∮ I'm with you either way ∮
∮ 再也没什么可失去 再也没有痛苦 ∮
∮ Nothing's lost, no more pain ∮
∮ 你赐予了我力量 ∮
∮ Just give me strength ∮
∮ 赐予了我力量 ∮
∮ Give me strength ∮
∮ 无论怎样我与你同在 ∮
∮ I'm with you either way ∮
∮ 再也没什么可失去 再也没有痛苦 ∮
∮ Nothing's lost, no more pain ∮
∮ 你赐予了我力量 ∮
∮ Just give me strength ∮